<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The practice of policy written by Lodowike Lloyd ...</title>
            <author>Lloyd, Lodowick, fl. 1573-1610.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16627</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1335</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22128141</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22128141</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9175</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68396)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9175)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1731:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The practice of policy written by Lodowike Lloyd ...</title>
                  <author>Lloyd, Lodowick, fl. 1573-1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Simon Stafford, dwelling in Hosier Lane, neere Smithfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedicated to King James I of England.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A² B-L⁴ M².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Political science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9175:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9175:1"/>
THE PRACTICE OF POLICY.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Lodowike Lloyd,</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Qui foueam fodit, incidet in eam: &amp; qui laqueum ponit, peribit in illo,</hi>
            </q>
            <bibl>Eccle. 27.</bibl>
            <q>
               <hi>Qui diſſipat ſepem, mordebit eum Coluber.</hi>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Simon Stafford, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Hoſier lane, neere Smithfield.</p>
            <p>1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9175:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9175:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the moſt high and mighty <hi>Prince, James, by the grace of God,</hi> King of England, Scotland, Fraunce <hi>and Ireland, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>RATERVS</hi> contending with <hi>Epheſtion</hi> (moſt gracious Prince) which of them two loued <hi>Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der</hi> beſt, appealed to the king for iudgement, who iudged that <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terus</hi> loued the king, and <hi>Epheſtion</hi> loued <hi>Alexander:</hi> but both alike loued <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the king. So the Brytaynes and the Engliſh loue your Maieſty in like ſort, that you can hardly iudge which of them loues you beſt, vnleſſe you do as <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> did, to iudge the Engliſh as <hi>Craterus,</hi> &amp; the Brytaynes as <hi>Epheſtion.</hi> but both Brytaines &amp; Engliſh with equall loue and loyalty loue King <hi>lames</hi> alike, that all hauing the like cauſe of ioy, all ſhould ſo reioyce to enioy ſuch a Iewell, that in one day enriched England &amp; Ireland with a king, and the whole Empire of Brytayne with a Prince, to whome it was reſerued and continued from <hi>Brutus</hi> the firſt King, to your Maieſty the ſecond King, not as to a ſtranger, but to a iuſt &amp; a lawfull king of the ſtocke and linage of <hi>Brutus,</hi> to ſucceed and ſit on <hi>Brutus</hi> ſeat 2800. yeeres after <hi>Brutus,</hi> where your Maieſty may better ſay then <hi>Caeſar, Veni, vidi, vici,</hi> for that you haue conquered Time, came to your owne kingdomes, and may ſee in your ſelfe ſuch a ſucceſsion, that neyther the Macedonians, who much bragged of their <hi>Hercules,</hi> whoſe lyne ended in <hi>Alexander:</hi> neyther the Romanes, who much gloried of <hi>Gens Iulia,</hi> whoſe ſtocke extincted in <hi>Nero:</hi> nor any nation vnder heauen (which can boaſt of their antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties moſt) can ſay ſo much.</p>
            <p>The Scythians with their Acornes in their heads, and the Athenians with their Graſſehoppers in their haires, may wel bragge of their Acornes and Graſſehoppers, but not of the like Empires: for as <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> ſayd to <hi>Pericles</hi> of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire
<pb facs="tcp:9175:3"/>
of Greece, ſo <hi>Cratippus</hi> ſpake to <hi>Pompey</hi> of the Romane Empire, that periods of times are limited.</p>
            <p>Embrace you therefore (moſt mighty Prince) the great bleſſings of God, which ſo embraced your Maieſty, &amp; elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you King, to gouerne his people, and to maintayne his lawes, without which, neither king nor kingdome can ſtand, for that is the rich Tablet, which <hi>Moſes</hi> brought from Mount Sinay, to ſet about Iſraels neck. It is that long ladder, which <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaw in his dreame at Bethel, that reached fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth into heauen: and it is that bright-ſhining Starre, which guyded the kings from the Eaſt, vnto Chriſt at Bethlehem.</p>
            <p>The only Pearle that we ſhould buy, and the only Iewel that wee ſhould weare, not as gards on our garments, or frontiers on our forheads, as the Iewes wore <hi>Phylacterium,</hi> but rather printed in our hearts, where we ought to giue thanks for our King, which for 50. yeeres haue bene without either King or Prince, and now wee enioy a King, a Queene, a Prince, and Princes, with no leſſe bleſſings by the comming of your Maieſty ouer the riuer Tweede, from Scotland to England, to incorporate both to the ancient name of great Brytaine, then by the comming of Iſrael from Meſopota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, ouer the riuer Iordan, to alter the name of Canaan into Iuda; whoſe poſterity, as they were wrought on <hi>Aarons</hi> garment, to remember Iſrael, ſo your princely progeny may bee ſure ſet on the vnſeamed coate of Chriſt, to remember the houſe of <hi>Iacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties moſt bounden and dutyfull ſeruant,
Lodowike Lloyd.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:9175:3"/>
            <head>THE PRACTICE <hi>OF POLICY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heodoricus,</hi> King of the <hi>Gothes,</hi> began <note place="margin">Theodori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</note> his letter, to the Senators of Rome, with a ſentence of <hi>Plato, That Nature might ſooner erre, then a Prince to frame a Common wealth vnlike to himſelfe.</hi> It is moſt true, <hi>Imperium oſtendit virum,</hi> for ſuch as the Magiſtrates are, ſuch are the people: ſuch as the Prince is, ſo are his ſubiects: and that was the cauſe, why <hi>Cyrus,</hi> King of Perſia, was <note place="margin">Cyrus.</note> ſo much honoured among the Perſians, for his wiſe lawes, graue gouernment, and great policy, in enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Monarchy of Perſia, in ſo much, that hee that reſembled <hi>Cyrus,</hi> if it were in any part of his body, or had but a crooked noſe, like <hi>Cyrus,</hi> hee was ſo eſteemed and made much of, in all Perſia, as hee ſhould haue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour <note place="margin">Leuin. li. 1 cap 15.</note> ſhewed him in any place, and in euery company. And ſo hee that had but a long head, like <hi>Pericles,</hi> in <note place="margin">Pericles.</note> Athens, his cauſe ſhould be heard before the Iudges of <hi>Areopagites,</hi> or before any Magiſtrates, in the Court <hi>Prytaneon,</hi> free, &amp; before other. Such was the law and fauour of the people towardes <hi>Pericles</hi> in Athens, and towardes <hi>Cyrus</hi> in Perſia, that the Midwiues, and Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, both in Aſia, and in Greece, had in charge giuen them by the parents, to do their beſt indeuor to frame
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:9175:4"/>
and to mould their young infants, like <hi>Cyrus</hi> in Perſia, and like <hi>Pericles</hi> in Athens: yet few (though the Nurſes did their indeuours) were found in Athe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, like <hi>Pericles,</hi> vnleſſe it were with a long head: and fewe, or none, were found in Perſia, like <hi>Cyrus,</hi> vnleſſe it were with a <note place="margin">Cyrus. Val. max. l. 9. ca. 14. Plin. li. 7. cap. 12.</note> crooked noſe. This kind of likeneſſe is found in many. So was <hi>Artenon</hi> like to <hi>Antiochus</hi> the great: and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagenis,</hi> a Cooke, like to <hi>Strabo Pomp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore that noble Roman, <hi>Pompey,</hi> being yet but a very young man, (heating by common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, that he much reſembled <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, in countenance, geſtures, and outward behauiours, but ſpecially likened to <hi>Alexander,</hi> for the growing of his hayres vpwardes vpon his forehead: in which ſome write, that <hi>Alexander, Hector,</hi> and <hi>Pompey,</hi> much reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled <note place="margin">Alex. Hect. and Pomp. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pisthocomae</note> one the other:) this noble Captaine, I ſay, eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med little to be like <hi>Alexander</hi> in externall forme and frame of his body, but he exerciſed, how he might imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate <hi>Alexander,</hi> to be like to him in qualities, and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the minde, <hi>Non ex apparatu, ſed ex animo reges:</hi> ſo that he imitated <hi>Alexander</hi> in valour and magnanimitie of minde, and not in forme of his body.</p>
            <p>By ſuch meanes, <hi>Pompey</hi> became afterward to bee compared, and was called <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great, after hee <note place="margin">Pompey.</note> had ſubdued <hi>Sertorius</hi> in Affrica, as <hi>Alexander</hi> the great was called in Perſia, after he had ſubdued <hi>Darius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was a more laudable imitation in <hi>Pompey,</hi> then in the great men and Captaynes of Macedonia, who would wiſh nothing more then to bee called <hi>Opistho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comae,</hi> for ſo the Grecians called <hi>Alexander,</hi> for that his haires vpon his forhead grew vpward: but good Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes muſt not be like the Macedonian Captaynes,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:9175:4"/>
following onely <hi>Alexander,</hi> to be called <hi>Opisthocomae:</hi> but like <hi>Pompey,</hi> imitating <hi>Alexander</hi> in greatneſſe and valour of minde. There were many <hi>Opisthocomae</hi> in Macedonia, &amp; yet not one like <hi>Alexander:</hi> many croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked noſes in Perſia, but not one like <hi>Cyrus</hi> &amp; many that had long heads in Athens, and yet not one like <hi>Pericles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> the Philoſopher writ vnto his M. the great <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Ariſt. pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. ad Alex, Plut. in Demet.</note> 
               <hi>Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der,</hi> of another likenes that ſhould be in a Prince; that it was more Princely for a King, to haue a noble mynde endued with noble vertues, then a gallant body furniſhed with gay Garments, like <hi>Demetrius,</hi> who had more care of his Aſtrologicall cloake, then of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to hang the world on his backe, then to thinke in his minde of his people: Like <hi>Nero,</hi> who ware no Garment twiſe, but dayly new-inuented Garments. Or like <hi>Caligula,</hi> who ware <hi>Sacras Deorum Veſtes,</hi> to ſet foorth the greatneſſe of his Authority. Theſe were <hi>Reges ex Veſtibus, non ex Virtutibus:</hi> For the moſt part of Heathen kings, ſtudying how to pleaſe the people with outward ſhew and pompe, would paint their faces and anoynt their eyes, to ſeeme to bee of greater Maieſtie with their Subiects.</p>
            <p>So the Kings and Peeres of Ethiopia, were wont to bee anoynted with Vermillion, that they might ſeeme young and fayre, to be amiable vnto the people.</p>
            <p>The Kings of Aſſiria vſed to anoynt their eyes and <note place="margin">Alex. lib. 6. cap. 6.</note> to paint their faces, with like policy, to entiſe blind and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people to eſteeme them rather gods then men, according to king <hi>Cyrus</hi> Decree, for that they held their Crownes vnder <hi>Cyrus:</hi> For then the Perſians had all other kings vnder their obeiſance, as the Romanes had afterward: And therfore <hi>Cyrus</hi> made a Lawe, that the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9175:5"/>
great Kings of Perſia, in any Feaſt or Triumph, ſhould anoynt their faces <hi>adipe Leonino,</hi> that they might ſeeme more manly and more Princely, to allure the people to accept their greatneſſe, and to ad nyre the Maieſtie of their preſence.</p>
            <p>They write, that <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> was inſtructed with <note place="margin">Auguſtus Caeſar.</note> 
               <hi>Cyrus</hi> Lawes, for in his third Tryumph he vſed the like: whether it was for loue or for feare, his countenance terrified the Army of <hi>M. Antonius</hi> in the Battayle of <hi>Actium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet among theſe Heathens, there were many that deſpiſed thoſe externall ſhewes and pompe.</p>
            <p>Such a one was <hi>Ageſilaus,</hi> among the Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians: <hi>Epaminondas,</hi> among the Thebanes: and <hi>Fabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi> among the Romanes.</p>
            <p>It is hiſtoried, that <hi>Germanicus</hi> the Emperour was ſo amiable and louing in ſight, becauſe in ſight he ſeemed <note place="margin">Germani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</note> ſo plaine a Prince in Apparrell, ſo plauſible &amp; ſo gentle in ſpeache, for that hee was a ſingular wiſe Prince, that they that ſaw him and heard him, were ſo addicted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; that he was ſo beloued of his Subiects, ſo mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified of his Nobles, that it was neuer heard, that <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manicus</hi> was eyther hated of the one, or enuied of the other: Such is the force of Vertue, <hi>Si cerni potuit oculis,</hi> ſayth <hi>Plato,</hi> that it would mooue much affection and loue in men by looking: the like ſayth <hi>Cicero:</hi> the Report of vertuous men whom wee neuerſaw, doeth <note place="margin">Cic. de nat. Deo. li. 1.</note> breed ſuch affection, that good men are deſirous to ſee them.</p>
            <p>The preſence of a good and a godly Prince is great, and ſo great, that the Prayer and preſence of king <hi>Abia</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Chron. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 13. 14</note> ouerthrew 500000. Iſraelites: The Prayer and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:9175:5"/>
of king Aſa, ouerthrew <hi>Zerath</hi> the Ethiopian king <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Plat. in Apophth.</note> with his great Army of ten hundreth thouſand: and therefore <hi>Antigonus,</hi> hearing one of his Lieutenants and Captaynes ſaying, that the enemies (king <hi>Ptolomey</hi> his Army) were more in number then they, <hi>Antigonus</hi> ſeemed to bee angry and ſaid, How many doeſt thou number me for?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> was euer wont to ſay in any danger, by Sea or by Land to his Souldiers: <hi>Alexander</hi> is heere: <hi>Habetis Alexandrum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So often would <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſay in any peril, Ye haue <hi>Caeſar</hi> &amp; his fortunes with you: ſo he ſaid to <hi>Amyclas</hi> his pilot.</p>
            <p>It was an vſuall ſpeache of the people of Sparta, to aſke where the enemyes were? and not to aske, how many they were?</p>
            <p>But we leaue thoſe Princes to Fortune, <hi>Qui plura Fortunae quàm virtuti tribuunt.</hi> The greateſt praiſe and commendations of Chriſtian Princes muſt not be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the Actions of Fortune, as the Heathen Princes doo, but to the benfites of Vertue, who by the greatneſſe of their wiſdome and vertue, haue their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from God. For the Crowne, the Scepter, and the Kingdome it ſelfe is from God, who made them ſo great, that he called them Goddes, ſaying: <hi>Ye are Gods on earth:</hi> but how? <hi>Pietate et iuſtitia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Augustine.</hi> And ſo in <hi>Plato,</hi> a King is called, <hi>Deus quiſpiam huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus;</hi> and yet in <hi>Homer,</hi> a King is called but <hi>Paſtor populi:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and the King of Kings, is called the great Shepheard: for a king ought to haue as great care ouer his people, as a ſhepherd ouer his ſheep. <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperor ſaid, <hi>Rempub. non eſse ſuam, ſed ſe Reip.</hi> For as without a King, neither towne, city, country or kingdome can ſtand:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9175:6"/>
ſo ought a King to gouerne and rule his ſubiects, that he may deſerue the name of a King, &amp; not of a Tyrant: <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Xenoph. ped. 9.</note> for it is fit, ſaith <hi>Cyrus,</hi> that a Gouernour muſt farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell thoſe whom he gouerneth in vertue &amp; wiſdome. Such as <hi>Caleb</hi> was with <hi>Ioſua,</hi> and ſuch as <hi>Iethro</hi> was with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſuch as <hi>Nathan</hi> was with <hi>Dauid:</hi> If ſuch wiſe Counſellers attend vpon Kings in Court, that Court ſhall flouriſh, and that Common-wealth ſhall proſper.</p>
            <p>Wiſe men in Court with Princes, are as Preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues kept for a ſicke body. That made <hi>Salomon</hi> to aske for wiſdome onely to gouerne his people. That made <hi>Vliſſes</hi> to crie out in <hi>Homer</hi> to <hi>Minerua, Si te Diua Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerua</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. Odyſſ.</note> 
               <hi>vtar:</hi> If I can haue thy company, O Goddeſſe, I eſteeme not who wil be againſt me. That made <hi>Pericles</hi> to forſake his youthfull companies, &amp; to haue ſage and wiſe men about him, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he in Athens ſucceeded <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtocles</hi> in publike gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Athenians: And that made <hi>Dion</hi> to ſpeak of <hi>Plato,</hi> hauing had proofe of <note place="margin">Dions ſpeach of Plato.</note> 
               <hi>Platoes</hi> wiſdom &amp; counſell, <hi>Mallem vnum Platonem, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mille Antimachos:</hi> For <hi>Plato</hi> gaue ſuch counſell to <hi>Dion,</hi> not to pleaſe, but to profit <hi>Dion.</hi> Such cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel gaue <hi>Solon</hi> to the Athenians, <hi>Non quae ſuauiſsima, ſed quae optima.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But good counſel is often reiected. <hi>Ieremy</hi> gaue good <note place="margin">3. Reg. cap. 12. Good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell.</note> counſell to King <hi>Zedechias,</hi> but hee reiected it. <hi>Lot</hi> gaue good counſell to the Sodomites, but they regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it not. The Elders of Iſrael gaue good counſell to <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> but hee eſteemed it not. Wiſdome crieth out in the ſtreets, &amp; offreth her ſeruice free vnto Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and yet ſome Princes regard her not: But truely that Prince is happy, where wiſdome may ſay, <hi>Habito in conſilijs:</hi> That wiſdom guided <hi>Noah</hi> in the Arke: that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9175:6"/>
wiſdome inſtructed the Patriarkes before the Law, to liue vnder the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iephtha</hi> ſhewed himſelfe a wiſe man, and gaue wiſe <note place="margin">Iephtha.</note> counſel to his Captaines, how they might find out the falſe Ephramites from the true Iſraelites, by pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the letter <hi>Shiboleth;</hi> and that before the Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites <note place="margin">Iud. 12.</note> ſhould paſſe ouer Iorden, leſt they ſhould gather head againſt the Iſraelites againe.</p>
            <p>Great wiſdome it is to looke in time to ſuch, and to cut off the heads of them that would willingly haue many heads like Hidra. I wiſh there were no heads of Hidra yet lurking in any Engliſh Laerna.</p>
            <p>Thus was <hi>Iephtha</hi> called from the land of Tob, and <hi>Gedeon</hi> from the Barne-threſhing, to kill and deſtroy <note place="margin">Gedeon.</note> theſe wicked Madianites, and falſe Ephramites, which were ſcattered and diſperſed into all partes of the world.</p>
            <p>Was not <hi>Dauid</hi> called fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Shepheard, to be anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">Dauid, a Shepheard</note> king in Iſrael by <hi>Samuel,</hi> while yet <hi>Saul</hi> liued, for the ſinnes of <hi>Saul,</hi> and to ouerthrow the houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> for all the practice and policy of <hi>Saul</hi> to the contrary?</p>
            <p>Was not <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> the ſeruant of <hi>Salomon,</hi> called &amp; <note place="margin">Ieroboam, a ſeruant.</note> anoynted king in Iſrael, by the Prophet <hi>Ahias,</hi> in the time of <hi>Salomon</hi> &amp; of his ſonne <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> and to take ten of the twelue Tribes from <hi>Salomon?</hi> And was not <hi>Iehu,</hi> from a ſoldier, called and anoynted king by <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iehu, a ſoldier.</note> ſeruant, while <hi>Achab</hi> yet reigned in Iſrael, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy <hi>Achab</hi> and all his poſterity, for the Idolatry of <hi>Achab?</hi> The iuſt iudgement of God againſt wicked Princes. And ſo in other like practiſers, that ſeek by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy to ouerthrow kingdomes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul,</hi> with all his policy, with his ſonnes, his ſeruants,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9175:7"/>
and his daughter that he maried to <hi>Dauid,</hi> onely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue <hi>Dauid,</hi> could not preuent <hi>Dauid</hi> of the kingdom. It was the purpoſe of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salomon,</hi> for all his wiſedome and royalty, and his friends, could not hinder <hi>Ieroboam</hi> his ſeruant from the kingdome. It was ſo determined.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Achab,</hi> with all his gods and Idols, could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent <hi>Iehu,</hi> nor take reuenge vpon <hi>Elizeus,</hi> no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Benhadad,</hi> king of Syria could feed his wrath vpon <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeus:</hi> no policy, no practice, no cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel againſt the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elizeus,</hi> looking in the face of <hi>Hazael,</hi> ſaid, that hee ſhould be king after <hi>Benhadad</hi> in Syria, &amp; withall wept, knowing how he would ſtrangle his maſter <hi>Benhadad,</hi> the king, and how Tyrant-like he would plague Iſrael, during the time of his cruell gouernment. Many had cauſe to weepe, if men knewe, as <hi>Elizeus</hi> did, what po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies are practiſed in many mens hearts.</p>
            <p>And therefore had olde <hi>Oſiris,</hi> king of Egypt, the <note place="margin">Oſiris his ſcepter.</note> likenes of a mans eye in the vpper end of his Scepter, to ſignifie, that kings ſhould be circumſpect and wiſe, to ſee vnto the policy and practice of wicked men: for againſt ſuch wiſe and godly Princes, no policy can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, no more then a little cloud can darken the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Sunne. And as the Sunne with his brightnes lighteneth all the Sky, ſo doth a vertuous Prince with his wiſdome, his ſubiects: for ſo <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſayth, <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. Polit.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ſola virtus Principis, prudentia:</hi> The only vertue of a Prince, is to become wiſe, &amp; to chuſe ſuch Wiſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers, as <hi>Moyſes</hi> did of graue &amp; godly wiſe men (which counſell was called, <hi>synadrion)</hi> to help &amp; to ayd him in the gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of 600000. men, &amp; that in a wildernes.</p>
            <p>By counſel, Commonwealths &amp; Kingdomes ſtand:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9175:7"/>
So in <hi>Saluſt</hi> it is ſayd vnto <hi>Caeſar, Quò magis Imperium, cò maior cura:</hi> So long ſhal kingdoms proſper, while good Counſel gouernes: <hi>Dum apud eos vera conſilia valueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:</hi> For (ſayd <hi>Plato)</hi> All good and godly Counſayles are <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſacred, according to that which Chriſt ſayd: Where two or three are gathered in my name, there am I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. It is neyther, ſayd <hi>Scipio</hi> to <hi>Micipſa,</hi> ſtrong armies, treaſures, nor golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Scepters that vphold king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, but truth, wiſedome, and Counſayle. So <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20.</note> ſayth vnto the great <hi>Alexander;</hi> that Counſel is <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Ariſt. Rhet. ad Alex. Suet. cap. 25. Auguſtus ſaying.</note> moſt diuine in matters of ſtates: for that hee was euer careful to haue <hi>Alexander</hi> gouerned by counſaile, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing well the greatneſſe of his minde, &amp; the conqueſt which he took in hand: Many periſh for want of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle, and many more for not accepting of counſell.</p>
            <p>Wiſe counſayle and the reward thereof, was more giuen in Sparta to the Captayne that ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the enemyes by policy and counſell, then by the ſword: for that attempt, ſayd <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> is not to bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſed, where more feare is in loſing, then hope in getting the victory.</p>
            <p>The Carthagineans ſo eſteemed wiſe counſel, that if any of their Captains had done any thing but by wiſe counſel, though they had obteyned great victories, the law in Carthage was, that they ſhould die. Great Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes wanne more by counſaile, then by the Sword: <hi>Pluraconſilio, quàm vi magnos Duces perfeciſſe.</hi> Wiſe Princes muſt be like <hi>Ianus,</hi> looking backward as well as <note place="margin">Tacit. 11. Ann. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> forward.</p>
            <p>It was <hi>Sertorius</hi> ſaying to <hi>Pompey</hi> the great: <hi>Quod re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicere magis, quàm proſpicere oporteat Ducem.</hi> That a wiſe Gouernor looketh backward as well as forward: But
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9175:8"/>
Ambition ſayth <hi>Seneca,</hi> neuer looketh backe, but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <note place="margin">Plut. in Serto.</note> how hee may enterteyne factious and ſeditious men to hold him vp. They neuer thinke of their owne liues, when they imagine to preuent others of their liues: Sedition therfore is as dangerous to Kings in their kingdomes, as to Commaunders in Field in the Army. For ſo <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid, <hi>Idem ius habet aduerſus imperia, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aduerſus imperantes.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>Sectio. 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ERVIVS GALBA, vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence <note place="margin">Oroſ. lib. 5 cap. 21.</note> of doing of ſome great good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Luſitanians, aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled the chiefeſt men, &amp; the gallanteſt Youths of three great Cities, to the nomber of ſeuen thouſand, whome hee moſt treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly and falſly ſlewe: which mooued great Sedition and tumult in Spaine againſt the Romanes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haſtrubal,</hi> intending, vnder the colour of hunting, to inuade Numidia, being reſiſted by the Numidians, told them hee came but to hunt Elephants.</p>
               <p>By the like policy of hunting, <hi>Hanibal</hi> got Tarentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>Such a hunter was <hi>Nymrod,</hi> that hunted kings and kingdomes, and therefore he was called, The mighty <note place="margin">Gen. 10.</note> Hunter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ninus</hi> was a great hunter of kingdoms &amp; countries.</p>
               <p>So may it be ſaid of <hi>Cyrus</hi> and of <hi>Alexander:</hi> ſo great hunters were they, that they died in their hunting out of their kingdomes.</p>
               <p>Hunting is a military exerciſe, which made <hi>Sertorius</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Plut. in Serto.</note>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:9175:8"/>
to vſe hunting, and to trauaile the hard rockes of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica; and that he and his ſoldiers thereby might better indure labour and payne againſt the Romanes, hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted them ſo much with hunting, that they were able to ſuſtayne any hardneſſe.</p>
               <p>The cauſe therefore why <hi>Braſidas</hi> compared hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to warre, was, for that the like ſtratagems are often inuented and executed in warres againſt ſoldiers, as the Hunter doeth againſt diuers kindes of beaſts, ſpecially in <hi>Venatione Circenſi,</hi> at Rome; or in hunting of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants, Lyons, Tigers, and ſuch other wilde beaſtes, where the policy and ſtratagems of the Hunter, as the force and courage of the ſoldiers, muſt be.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mithridates,</hi> King of Pontus, to auoyd the ſnares <note place="margin">Iuſt. li. 37.</note> &amp; dangers of the enemy, gaue himſelfe ſo to hunting, that hee neither vſed City, Towne, or any houſes for ſeuen yeres together, ſo that by ſuch paynefull exerciſe he held tack with the Romanes for forty yeres. That was the cauſe why <hi>Cato</hi> preferred hunters and laborers <note place="margin">Cato de re ruſt. lib. 1.</note> fit for warres, <hi>Ex venatoribus &amp; agricolis milites ſtrenui gignuntur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We read in <hi>Xenophon,</hi> that young Gentlemen were brought vp, firſt in hunting, to make them more ſtrong and more able to indure the warres.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plato</hi> maketh mention of three kindes of hunting, <note place="margin">Pla. de leg.</note> 
                  <hi>Aquatilia, volatilia, ac terreſtria;</hi> but he much commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the laſt, <hi>Quadrupedia venari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This kind of hunting, <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperor ſo loued in his youth, that hee could ſpare no time about his owne buſineſſe, vntill he was better perſwaded by his counſell.</p>
               <p>So lawdable was this excerciſe, and very neceſſary
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:9175:9"/>
to ſouldiers, that <hi>Maximinus</hi> the Emperour vſed Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Legions to hunting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Domitianus</hi> a great Hunter, is much praiſed in <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius,</hi> and for nothing elſe, but for hunting; and yet he <note place="margin">Suet. in Dom. ca. 4.</note> hunted in Rome, as <hi>Haſtrubal</hi> did in Numidia, that all Rome might be his Fermors &amp; Tenants, and ſo to bee called <hi>Colonia Domitiana:</hi> that was the ſecret practice of <hi>Domitianus</hi> hunting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Probus</hi> the Emperour, is reported to cauſe his ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to plucke vp yong Okes by the roote, and to make the Theaters ſo large and wide, ſet and compaſſed with branches and boughes, that it ſeemed rather a Forreſt, or a Parke, then a Theater, that ſometime a thouſand Eſtriches, a thouſand Harts, a thouſand Lyons, a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Stagges, &amp; ſuch other fierce beaſts of Libia, were there hunted: ſo that ſuch hunting was called, <hi>Circen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces venationes,</hi> &amp; often vſed of the Emperors of Romes <note place="margin">Suet. in Oct. ca. 4. 5</note> inſomuch as they made Theaters round before, to ſee playes: and afterward, the Romans made them Amphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theaters long &amp; wyde, to ſee hunting; that by hunting with beaſts, they might the more bolder, and with leſſe feare, fight with the enemy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Xenophon</hi> wrote a whole Booke in praiſe of Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, wherin he named the greateſt Kings and warriers of the world, as <hi>Achilles, Cyrus, Alexander,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>But many of late, practiſed the like policy, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to hunt Elephants, but Lions and Vnicornes.</p>
               <p>In Mount <hi>Parthenius,</hi> there was a Temple dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Pan,</hi> and therein was a place named <hi>Aula,</hi> as it were a Sanctuary to all kinde of Beaſtes being hunted eyther by Lyons, Beares, or Wolues: if they could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer this place AVLA, they were ſafe: and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9175:9"/>
might they be folowed by thoſe Lyons, Beares, or Wolues. Such credit had they in their god <hi>Pan,</hi> that he could ſaue all Beaſtes that fled for ſuccour thyther, whether they came from Spaine, Italy, or from any where elſe.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Aetolia,</hi> there was a Wood conſecrated to <hi>Diana,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Alex. lib. 4. cap. 2.</note> that Dogges hunting after any Beaſt, when they came <hi>ad lucum Dianae,</hi> the ſacred wood of <hi>Diana,</hi> they ſtaid and could hunt no further.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> writes of the lyke place in the Mountaine, which the Greekes call <hi>Menalus,</hi> to which place if any wilde Beaſtes were hunted by Dogges, and could reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> this mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine, they were ſafe as though they were in Sanctuary; the Dogges neyther could nor would follow any further.</p>
               <p>Some kinde of Dogges there are more bloudy, that will ſo follow their game, that neither the Temple of <hi>Pan,</hi> nor the ſacred wood of <hi>Diana,</hi> nor the mountayne <hi>Menalus,</hi> nor yet <hi>Aula Regia,</hi> can ſtop their eagernes, like the Dogges of <hi>Actaeon,</hi> that wil deuoure their owne Maſter.</p>
               <p>Theſe be the ſeede of <hi>Caligula,</hi> that ſeeke not onely to cut off the necke of Rome at one blowe, as <hi>Caligula</hi> wiſhed, but the necke and head of England, Scotland, and Ireland.</p>
               <p>Theſe be the broode of Centaures, that dippe their weapons in the bloud of <hi>Neſſus:</hi> Theſe are they that conceiue miſchiefe, and bring ſoorth iniquity.</p>
               <p>Theſe be they (ſayth the Prophet) that hatch Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>katrice <note place="margin">Eſay 59.</note> egges, and hee that eateth of their egges, dyeth, and that which is trodden vpon, breaketh out vnto a Serpent, and becommeth a more deadly Serpent, then
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9175:10"/>
the Serpents of Arabia or Affrica, whatſoeuer is come from them, is poyſon, and bringeth death.</p>
               <p>Theſe wicked ones, are like the raging ſeas that can not reſt, whoſe waues caſt vp nothing but myre and <note place="margin">Eſay 59.</note> durt.</p>
               <p>Theſe wicked men be they that weaue the Spiders webbe, and yet ſhall not they couer themſelues with garments of their owne labour.</p>
               <p>Their Lawes, their peace, their fayre words, &amp; their fowle hearts, are nothing els but <hi>Ius ſine Iure in Armis:</hi> and therfore, it was the wiſh of <hi>Apollonius Thianae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> to know good men and to auoyde euyll men, who can not change their accuſtomed wickednes, no more then the Blacke-more can change his ſkynne, or the Leopard his ſpottes. <note place="margin">Iorem. 13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Next Hunting is Swimming, accounted for a Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary exerciſe, both to ſwymme to the enemy, as alſo to eſcape from the enemy by ſwymming, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> did in <note place="margin">Vig. lib. 1. cap. 10. Diodor. lib. 17.</note> the Watres at Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dria, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he followed after <hi>Pompey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander,</hi> at the Riuer <hi>Acinaſes,</hi> when there was no hope of helpe to ſaue his life, put off his Armour vnto his ſhirt, and made himſelfe ready to ſaue his life by ſwymming.</p>
               <p>Great ouerthrowes haue bene giuen to thoſe that could not ſwymme; as <hi>Niceas</hi> the Generall of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians, at the Riuer <hi>Aſinarus,</hi> where many of his ſouldiers, for want of skill to ſwimme, were ſlayne in the Ryuer by the Siracuſans. And this want of skill in ſwymming, often hindered <hi>Cyrus</hi> and his ſouldiers in many enterpriſes, as <hi>Xenophon</hi> ſayth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:9175:10"/>
               <head>Sectio 3.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>VBLIVS SCIPIO</hi> in Lidia, after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuall fowle weather day and night, and <hi>Antiochus,</hi> when he thought to relieue his wearied and wet ſouldiours, were then ſet vpon and ouerthrowen by <hi>Scipio</hi> and his Army.</p>
               <p>We read that <hi>Hanibal,</hi> after that he was dryuen out <note place="margin">Vid. Hani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal lib 1. cap 5.</note> of Affrica vnto Aſia by the Romanes, taught the kings of Aſia all policyes and ſtratagems, and counſayled <hi>Antiochus</hi> the great, in his Counſelles againſt the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, to throw great veſſelles full of quicke Vipers into the ſhips of the enemyes, that the Romanes, being frighted with theſe Vipers, might be hindered of their fight, and daunted of their courage.</p>
               <p>So did <hi>Antiochus,</hi> who imitated <hi>Hanibals</hi> counſel, but to no effect.</p>
               <p>So did <hi>Pruſias</hi> king of Bythinia, but to no effect; for victory commeth from the Lord.</p>
               <p>I commend both <hi>Antiochus</hi> and <hi>Pruſias,</hi> in follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing <hi>Hanibals</hi> directions againſt the Romanes, being their enemies: for theſe were lawfull ſtratagems to bee vſed againſt enemies: but to throw theſe Vipers into the faces of our friends, yea, into the faces of Kings &amp; Princes, vnto the deſtruction of our country, this is the practiſe of Sathan and of his ſouldiers, who euer haue bene moſt ſeditious in all good common wealths, farre worſe then the Snakes of Syria, which will not bite <note place="margin">The ſnakes of Syria.</note> their countrymen in Syria, though they find them out ſleeping: but better &amp; fitter to be likened to the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions in the mountaine <hi>Altenius</hi> in Caria, who are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious &amp; moſt perillous to their countrymen, ſparing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:9175:11"/>
none, yet to ſtraungers neuer hurtfull.</p>
               <p>As in Alexandria, between the Iewes and the Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, <note place="margin">Sedition betweene the Iewes, and the Grecians in Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria.</note> ſuch ſeditions grewe firſt by priuate men, that it came to publike warres after. Between the Samaritans and the Galileans grew ſuch ſedition, for that the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans wold not ſuffer the Galilea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to paſſe through their territories vnto the feaſt at Ieruſalem, according to the cuſtome of the Iewes. Such ſlaughter and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grew between the Iewes and the Samaritans, that neither <hi>Camaus</hi> the Romane Preſident, neither <hi>Numi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Quadratus</hi> the Preſident of Syria, might que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch this furious rage &amp; ſedition between the Iewes and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans. One ſparkle of fire burneth a whole Citie: &amp; one ſeditious man is dangerous in a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monwealth.</p>
               <p>And therfore, the Athenians vſed lawfull policy, to preuent their enemyes the Lacedemonians, arming a certen nomber of men in Garments like women, vpon a ſolemne feaſt day which the Athenians kept to <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerua,</hi> out of Athens: the Lacedemonians ſuppoſing to find them for their ſlaughter, were preuented with this ſtratage<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for women, they found men, armed with wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, <note place="margin">Front. lib. 4. cap. 7.</note> vnder the forme and ſhape of women, and were thereby ouerthrowen by the Athenians, and forced to returne with ſtrokes to Lacedemon. A lawfull prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of policy to preuent knowen enemyes.</p>
               <p>God taught the Iſraelites a ſtratagem, after they were ouerthrowne twiſe, the third time to ouerthrow the <note place="margin">Iud. 20.</note> Beniamites.</p>
               <p>So with the like policy, was <hi>Sempronius Gracchus</hi> with his Romane Legion by <hi>Vaccei,</hi> a people in Spaine, put to flight, by putting the moſt valianteſt men they had, in womens apparell, in Chariots and Coaches; the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9175:11"/>
Romanes imagining them to be women, ſuppoſing to haue a great prey thereby, came as though they ſhould eaſely take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away into their campe: but the Romans were forced to retyre to their Campe with loſſe, &amp; not with gayne, which they looked to haue. Such practiſes are often vſed, &amp; often preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by the enemies: but to practiſe any policy againſt our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, was euer odious.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phocion,</hi> a man of good eſtate, &amp; of beſt deſert among the Athenians, who had bin in times paſt Generall for the Athenians, yet being condemned of ſome ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted treaſon, might not bee buryed in Athens, but was carryed out of <hi>Attica terra</hi> to be buryed. It was not hard in Greece to finde out ſuch practiſers, for that all <note place="margin">Val. lib. 5. cap. 3.</note> the Cities in Greece were ſo enuious one vnto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they practiſed nothing elſe, but to deſtroy one another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Milciade,</hi> the Athenian, who wan ſuch great fame by killing many thouſand Perſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s at the battel of Maratho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet being dead in priſon, ſuſpected of treaſon, his ſonne <hi>Cymon,</hi> that renowned Grecian, became moſt willingly a priſoner for his father, to haue his buriall in Athens: of which, <hi>Cymon</hi> would often brag, that he obtained his fathers Patrimony, <hi>Carcerem et Catenas:</hi> for there was a Law in Athens, that if there were any, <hi>Qui de Repub. malè meriti ſunt,</hi> which might not bee found true vnto their Countrey, they ſhould dye in Athens, but not be buried (according to the Law) at Athens. So horrible is treaſon, and ſo odious were Traytors in Athens.</p>
               <p>Such a Law was in Egypt againſt their kings, that if they ſhould offend in any great capitall cryme againſt the publike ſtate, they ſhould giue accompt before the thirty Iudges of Egypt, before they ſhould bee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9175:12"/>
buried in Pyramides: which was the moſt odious thing in Egypt, for their Kings to want burial, and therefore, <hi>Simandius,</hi> an ancient king, had a rich Tablet hangd vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his breſt, whereon was ſet the picture of Iuſtice; which <note place="margin">Diod. lib. 2. cap. 1.</note> Monument, after his time, <hi>Simandius</hi> left to his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the kings of Egypt, that they might be put in mind, by looking vpon the picture of Iuſtice, to do iuſtice.</p>
               <p>Wicked <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> practiſing treaſon, came to <hi>Godolia,</hi> whom the king of Babylon made Gouernour ouer the Cities of Iuda, and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> did eate, and was feaſted at <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere. 40.</note> 
                  <hi>Godolias</hi> table, and after ſlewe him with the ſword, and al the Iewes that were with <hi>Godolia</hi> at Miſpha, of meere enuy, which is the cauſe of all reuenge.</p>
               <p>So the two Porters of king <hi>Ahaſhueroſh,</hi> that kept his gate, conſpired againſt their Maſter, and both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented <note place="margin">Heſter 2.</note> to kill the king, had not <hi>Mardocheus</hi> the Iew pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haman,</hi> ſo enuying <hi>Mardocheus,</hi> that he could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the ſight of him, practiſed policy, firſt with the king, againſt the Iewes, and after, he conſulted with his wife, how he might deſtroy <hi>Mardocheus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caeſar,</hi> with the like enuy, after long doubting of his marching in armes as an enemy vnto Rome, his owne countrey, yet at length being ouercome with deſire of reuenge, ſayd, <hi>Iacta eſt alea,</hi> being reſolued to reuenge his malice againſt <hi>Pompey,</hi> to plague Rome, and to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his Countrey. A man (ſayth <hi>Salomon)</hi> deuiſeth <note place="margin">Pro. 16.</note> a way in his heart: but it is the Lord that ordereth his doings: the lottes are caſt into the lappe: but the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering thereof ſtandeth in the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:9175:12"/>
               <head>Sectio 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Achior</hi> had ſaid, that great was the power of the God of Iſrael, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lophernes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iudeth 5.</note> and his Captaynes would haue ſlayne him, like the Scribes and Phariſees, who fretted and fumed to heare the people cry, <hi>Hoſanna</hi> to the <note place="margin">Math. 21.</note> King of kings the Sonne of God. But the Lord findeth out the policy &amp; practice of ſuch wicked men: for ſo he found out the practice &amp; policy of <hi>Cain</hi> (who vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour <note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> of walking vnto the field, did kill his brother <hi>Abel)</hi> by aſking a queſtion: Where is thy brother <hi>Abel?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord alſo found out the practice and policy of <hi>Eſau</hi> towards his brother <hi>Iacob,</hi> who ſaid in his heart: <hi>Occidam fratrem meum</hi> Iacob. <note place="margin">Gen. 27.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> demaunding of his brethren, what became of their other two brethren, made <hi>Ruben</hi> confeſſe to his brethren, that the Lord had found out their wicked practice.</p>
               <p>What treaſon, what murther, though long kept ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret by men, but was eyther by Byrdes of the ayre, or Stones of the ſtreete found out and deſcribed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Achilles,</hi> very craftily practiſing policy to hide himſelf in a womans garment in Greece, leſt he ſhould go with <hi>Agamemnon</hi> to the warres in Phrygia, was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out by the policie and craft of <hi>Vliſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vliſſes</hi> likewiſe fayning himſelfe mad (through the like policy to ſtay in Ithaca, with his fayre wife <hi>Pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lope)</hi> his practice was found out by <hi>Palamedes. Sic Ars deluditur arte</hi> among men.</p>
               <p>If practices of men by men are found out, where
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9175:13"/>
ſhall the Traytour or the murtherer hide his practice &amp; wicked policy from the knowledge of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> could not hide it in Paradiſe, nor <hi>Lucifer</hi> in Heauen, nor <hi>Ionas</hi> in the bottome of the Sea: Where ſhall a man flye from the preſence of God, that is of a guilty Conſcience?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1.</note>It made <hi>Cain</hi> to ſay: <hi>Omnis qui inuenerit me, occidet me.</hi> It made <hi>Ionas</hi> to ſay to the Saylers to Tharſis: <hi>Tollite &amp; mittite me in mare:</hi> And it made <hi>Iudas</hi> to ſay, <hi>Tradidi ſanguinem iuſtum,</hi> and to hang himſelfe.</p>
               <p>It makes a number to hang, to drowne, and to kill the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, prouoked therto by a tormented conſcience.</p>
               <p>For we reade both in Diuine and prophane Hyſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that more lewd and wicked men come from good men, then good men from the wicked: So that, of one <hi>Cateline,</hi> being a wicked man in Rome, became ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wicked <hi>Catelines,</hi> that Rome had too many <hi>Catelines,</hi> ſo full of ſpite and enuy vnto Rome, that they were (as <hi>Saluſt</hi> ſaith) <hi>Impuri animi Dijs hominibuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> infeſti.</hi> And ſo likewiſe, in Athens, of one hatefull <hi>Tymon,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Miſantropos,</hi> grew ſo many odious <hi>Tymons,</hi> that there were too many <hi>Tymo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> in Athe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. But we leaue theſe <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telines</hi> in Rome, &amp; theſe <hi>Tymons</hi> in Athens, and we wiſh that there were neither <hi>Catelines</hi> nor <hi>Tymons</hi> in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</p>
               <p>There were at Rome in S. <hi>Ieromes</hi> time, certayne <note place="margin">S. Ieromes ſaying of Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in Rome.</note> Engliſhmen, of good conſtitution and faire complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: whom when S. <hi>Ierom</hi> ſaw, he ſaid, <hi>Iſti Angli Angeli dici poſſunt.</hi> How ſtrange is it, that of that Nation, then called in Rome Angels, by St. <hi>Ierome,</hi> there ſhould be now ſome in England, which might be called Deuils, in whome are ſuch wicked practices, and ſuch lewd polycies, as neyther <hi>Philip</hi> of Macedon, againſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:9175:13"/>
the Graecians, nor <hi>Hannibal</hi> of Carthage, againſt the Romanes, could exceede them with their Military ſtratagems, which was lawfull againſt forreigne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes?</p>
               <p>The cauſe, ſayth <hi>Lactantius,</hi> of ſuch rebellious minds in ſuch men, was, <hi>Non noſce ſupremum numen, &amp;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lact. lib. 3 luſt. li. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>illud non venerari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore, the chiefeſt care of a good Prince, ought to bee firſt vigilant about Gods Seruice. So could <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> the Heathen Phyloſopher ſay, <hi>Res</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ariſt. 5. Polit. c. 11</note> 
                  <hi>diuinas, &amp;c.</hi> For as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayeth, The Romans euer ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the ſeruing of their gods, to be rather the cauſe of their Victories and Tryumphes ouer Affrica and Aſia, then their ſtrength and courage: and therefore, <hi>Maecenas</hi> wrote to <hi>Auguſtus</hi> the Emperor, to keepe and defend the Romane Religion, and the ſacred Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of their countrey to their gods, and not to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Egyptians, <hi>Qui variam et mixtam religionem co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luerunt,</hi> which accept of al kind of Religion, and neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent in one: for ſaith <hi>Cicero, Maioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſtituta tueri, &amp;c.</hi> It is wiſedome to defend the Lawes and decrees of the Elders, and the Religion of their Countrey: which to neglect, is ſacrilege.</p>
               <p>The Egyptians, though moſt ſuperſtitious and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous people, yet had they in their Temples in Greek written vpon the walles, <hi>Deus eſt quae ſunt, et quae non ſunt,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Her. in Pom. 5.</note> not much diſagreeing with the ſaying of the Apoſtle, <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> that God was he, by whom all things were done, and in whome, and from whom all good things proceed, and without him, nothing.</p>
               <p>It is not the Iuory Maces of the Romanes, nor the Ebony maces of the Indians, nor the Lyons &amp; Beares
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9175:14"/>
of the Babylonian, neyther the Dragons and Serpents of the Egyptian maces, that hold vp a kingdome: but the Scepter of Iuſtice. <hi>(Per me Reges regnant,</hi> ſayth the Lord.) <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Ethiopian Kings had their Scepter made in ancient time, in forme like a plough, in ſigne of huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, which ought to be maintayned by the king vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his people: for their kings were put in mind by their Scepters, to be carefull of their ſubiects, which are the ſtrength of the king.</p>
               <p>And ſo the old Perſian kings had their maces made <note place="margin">Diodor. li. 4. cap. 1.</note> like a ſpade, as the Ethiopians the plough, to put their kings in memory, that the plough &amp; the ſpade are the two onely Inſtruments moſt neceſſary in a common-wealth to enrich a king.</p>
               <p>Some other Heathen kings had vpon the tops of their maces, the figure of a Storke, to ſignifie piety and lenity in a Prince to be neceſſary; and vpon the nether end of the mace, the likeneſſe of <hi>Hippopotamus,</hi> that a <note place="margin">Hippopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamus, a Sea-horſe. Plut. in Alex.</note> Prince ſhould auoid fiercenes and wrath. Which had <hi>Alexander</hi> lookt vnto, as the Hiſtory ſayth, <hi>Nec Lyſima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus Leoni obiectus, nec Clytus haſta traiectus, nec Caliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenes mori iuſſus.</hi> Theſe three great murthers dimmed and obſcured his three great victories ouer Aſia, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, and Affricke, not then thinking of <hi>Caſſanders</hi> draught.</p>
               <p>For when <hi>Alexander</hi> would know of <hi>Calanus,</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Philoſopher, at his death, what hee would haue <hi>Alexander</hi> to do for him? Nothing, ſayd <hi>Calanus:</hi> and anſwered him, as the ſhaddow of <hi>Samuel</hi> anſwered <hi>Phetoniſsa</hi> for <hi>Saul,</hi> I ſhall ſhortly ſee you. So in <hi>Homer,</hi> doth <hi>Hector</hi> ſay, that <hi>Achilles</hi> ſhould be the next of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9175:14"/>
Greeke Captains that ſhould follow him. To be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant therefore in things to come, ſayd <hi>Cicero,</hi> is much better then to know them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> would haue bene moſt ſorrowfull, after he had wonne ſo many kingdomes, if he had knowne that he ſhould haue bene poyſoned in Babylon, before he had come to Macedonia. <hi>Achilles</hi> had no cauſe to reioyce, after his victories in Troy, if he had knowne, that he ſhould dye in Troy, and not in Greece. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Caeſar,</hi> after hee had ſubdued <hi>Pompey,</hi> if hee had knowen that he ſhould be ſlayne before the Image of <hi>Pompey</hi> in Rome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> being baniſhed from Rome, by <hi>M. Antonius,</hi> &amp; <note place="margin">Cicero his dreame. De diui. lib. 1.</note> being very penſiue &amp; ſad, the Image of <hi>C. Marius</hi> with the Sergeants before him, appeared as he was, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was laſt Conſull, enquiring of <hi>Cicero</hi> why he was ſo ſad, &amp; how he did. <hi>Cicero</hi> told <hi>Marius,</hi> for that he was forced to forſake Rome, by meanes of <hi>M. Antonius.</hi> The I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage tooke <hi>Cicero</hi> by the right hand, &amp; deliuered him to one of the Sergeants, and willed him to bring <hi>Cicero</hi> to his tombe, &amp; ſayd, that there he ſhould be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and relieued with great welcome. Theſe drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Practiſers, are often inſtructed by dreames, viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Idolatrous ſeruing of Images, which ſome haue in their houſes in England, as <hi>Alexander Seuerus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Alex. lib. 6. cap. 13</note> had in his gallery at Rome, the Images of <hi>Orpheus,</hi> of <hi>Apollonius,</hi> of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> and yet theſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages profit nothing, but to bring ſuch men to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> graue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tyberius,</hi> perceiuing that the whole Empire of Rome was weary of his life, hauing children of his owne, fearing his tyranny (by his conſcience moued)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9175:15"/>
ſhould be the cauſe, that none of them ſhould ſucceed him in the Empire, conſulted with auguratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherin himſelfe was welſeene, &amp; made ſupplication to his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey gods, as the maner &amp; rites of the Romans were, to giue him ſome certein ſigne, who ſhuld ſucceed him in the Empire: being aduertiſed, that the firſt that would come and ſalute him the next morning, ſhould ſucceed him in the Empire, cauſed preſently <hi>Euodus</hi> his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain to cal all his ſonnes to come in to him, to preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t others: but as <hi>Euodus</hi> went out of the chamber, came in <hi>Caeius,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Germanicus</hi> his brother, and ſaluted the Emperour: whereby he knew, that his diuination <note place="margin">Tiberlus deceiued by his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uination.</note> failed him, that none of his children ſhould ſucceede, but <hi>Caius,</hi> his brothers ſonne, according to <hi>Salomons</hi> ſaying, Man determineth, God diſpoſeth.</p>
               <p>Many in this age would faineknow the ſucceſſions of Empyres &amp; kingdoms: but they are not of wiſe mens opinions: <hi>Animi morbus eſt de his quaerere:</hi> That which is onely in God to know, is not fit for man to ſearch: for <note place="margin">Hermes. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ambitious men want no boughs to clime.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hannibal,</hi> perſwading king <hi>Pruſias</hi> to commence warre againſt the Romanes, anſwered <hi>Hannibal,</hi> that hee would enterpriſe nothing, before hee had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted with a Sooth-ſayer. To whome (ſaid <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal) Carunculae vitulinae mauis, quàm veteri Imperatori cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">De diui. lib. 2.</note> Canſt thou beleeue, king <hi>Pruſias,</hi> rather the lyuer of a beaſt, or the flying of a Fowle, then beleeue an olde Captaine, who had bin Generall againſt the Romanes 17. yeeres, who (to my loſſe) haue learned to be a Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour, &amp; can better counſell thee, then the Soothſayer?</p>
               <p>The likeſaying is tepbrted of king <hi>Mithridates,</hi> that in ſpite of fortune, after ſhe had done what ſhe could,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9175:15"/>
ſayd, I can counſel others not to truſt Fortune, though it be often true, <hi>Rara eſt Virtus, quam Fortuna non gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernat.</hi> But what is it but Superſtition wil do? Which made <hi>Cato</hi> to ſay and to wonder,<note place="margin">Lib. 2. de Diui.</note> 
                  <hi>Quod non rideret Aruſpex, Aruſpicem cum videret,</hi> that one Soothſayer would not laugh when he ſaw another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pub. Claudius,</hi> in the firſt Punicke watre, ieſting at ſo many Augurers, commaunded ſome Chickens that would eate nothing out of their Cage or Coupe, to be drowned in water, for that they might drinke, becauſe they would not eat, in contempt of their Diuination: but he was condemned to death by the people, for not eſteeming Auguration.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 2. de nat. Deo.</note>For the like cauſe, his fellow Conſull <hi>Lu. Iunius,</hi> to  eſcape the danger and wrath of the people, ſlew him ſelfe. <hi>Athens</hi> more ſuperſtitious then Rome, where <hi>Diagoras,</hi> was baniſhed, <hi>Socrates</hi> poyſoned, and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magoras</hi> impriſoned.</p>
               <p>Such Augurations and Soothſayings had bene in honor and worſhip in old time, and of ſuch credit, that it was death among the Romanes and the Perſians, to ieſt at it for their Magicke among the Perſians, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration among the Romanes, without which their kings could not be in times paſt elected.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scipio</hi> and <hi>Figulus,</hi> becauſe they were elected &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Magiſtrates, and not allowed by the Augurers <note place="margin">2. Diuin.</note> Lawes, being wrongfully created, they both refuſed &amp; forſooke their Offices, and were alſo reiected of the people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> after the reſtoring of an impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent cripple, being ſo borne of his mother, the people <note place="margin">Acts 3.</note> in Lyſtra cryed out, that Gods are come downe in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:9175:16"/>
the likeneſſe of men. And they called <hi>Paul, Mereu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> and <hi>Barnabas, Iupiter;</hi> and the Prieſts of <hi>Iupiter</hi> brought Bulles trymmed with Flowers and Garlands vnto the gates, where <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> lodged, and there would haue ſacrificed with the people.</p>
               <p>In like maner, one <hi>Demetrius,</hi> a Syluer-Smyth vnto <hi>Diana,</hi> ſtirred vp ſedition among the ſuperſtitious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſaying, that <hi>Paul</hi> perſwaded the people, not onely <note place="margin">Acts 19.</note> at Epheſus, but throughout all Aſia, that they bee not Gods which are made with hands: ſo that the Temple of the great Goddeſſe <hi>Diana,</hi> and the Image that came downe from <hi>Iupiter,</hi> ſhould be nothing eſteemed, and that her magnificence, which all Aſia and the whole world worſhipped, ſhould be deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>In Ieruſalem, their ſuperſtitious Idolatry was the onely cauſe of the ouerthrow of both the kingdomes of Iudah and of Iſrael, euery one worſhipping ſeuerall gods of ſtrange nations. And therefore the Prophet ſayd, That the Plummet of the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> &amp; the Line of Samaria, ſhould be ſtretched ouer Ieruſalem, that as Samaria was deſtroyed with her Idols, ſo ſhuld Ieruſalem with her Images.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> doth report of certeine Chaldean Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, being in his time at Rome, who ſhewed their cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <note place="margin">Cic. de Diuin. 2.</note> vpon three of the greateſt men of Rome, of equall fortune and greatnes, and therfore, one enuying the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, much doubting one of another, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſulted with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein Chaldeans then at Rome, by whom they were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified in the preſence of <hi>Cicero,</hi> that eche one of theſe 3. viz, <hi>Craſſus, Pompey,</hi> &amp; <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſhould liue to be very old, they ſhould dye in their houſes, &amp; ſhould with honor and fame accompliſh all their actions, wheras in truth,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9175:16"/>
they dyed afterwards otherwiſe, and that out of their countrey: <hi>Craſius</hi> firſt was ſlaine among the Parthians, and his head ſent by <hi>Surena</hi> to <hi>Pacorus,</hi> king of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians. <hi>Pompey</hi> was ſlaine in Egypt, and his head ſent by <hi>Ptolomy</hi> to <hi>Caeſar:</hi> And laſtly, <hi>Caeſar</hi> was ſlaine in the Senate houſe, among the Senators.</p>
               <p>Their dumme ſtratagems muſt be preuented, as <hi>Iehu</hi> did by the meſſenger of King <hi>Ioram,</hi> who came to <hi>Iehu,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">4. Reg. 9.</note> ſaying, Thus ſaith the king: Is it peace, <hi>Iehu?</hi> What haſt thou to do with peace, ſayth <hi>Iehu?</hi> come behind me &amp; follow me. What peace ſhould be, when factious and ſeditious men beareſway? or what peace can be, ſayd <hi>Iehu</hi> to king <hi>Iora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> whiles the whoredome of thy mother <hi>Iezabel,</hi> &amp; her witchcrafts are yet in great nomber; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iuda &amp; Iſrael agree not in one religion? When <hi>Achab</hi> and <hi>Baeals</hi> prieſts rule Iſrael, they muſt bee preuented, as <hi>Philip</hi> of Macedon did the Embaſſadors of the Etolia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, <note place="margin">Front. lib. 1. cap. 4.</note> who comming to entreat for peace, were kept in talking of peace, vntill king <hi>Philip</hi> had won Thermopyla, and placed his garriſon there.</p>
               <p>Theſe rebellious Practitioners haue, and alſo had their Embaſſadours alwayes abroade, to knowe if it bee peace, for them to come there, if they fayled of their purpoſe, which ſhould more feare God in their countrey, then feare their enemies out of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. But as <hi>Benhadad</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayled <hi>Iehoram,</hi> that he ſhould make ſtreets in Damaſco for him &amp; his people to dwel, <note place="margin">3. Reg 20</note> as his father made ſtreets in Samaria for the Aſſyrians to dwel, ſaying, My people ſhal be thy people: So Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belles were promiſed Townes and Citties to dwell in, and therfore ſaid they: <hi>Litet, ſilibet,</hi> to practiſe treaſon, murther and ſacriledge.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:9175:17"/>
There were many <hi>Antigonies</hi> in Greece: one <hi>Antigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Many An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonies in Greece.</note> ſurnamed <hi>Gonatus,</hi> for that one knee was bigger the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another: all his care was to make both his knees of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall proportion, that it might ſeeme vnto the people but of one quantitie.</p>
               <p>Another <hi>Antigonus,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Polyorcetes,</hi> for that he was alwayes practiſed buſily to ouerthrow townes and cities, and to triumph in his tyranny: hee would euer boaſt and bragge what euill hee had done, reioycing <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c.</note> much in titles of violence and of his conqueſts, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Greekes were wont to do, but none of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and iuſtice, but onely <hi>Ariſtides.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another <hi>Antigonus,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Doſan,</hi> for that he wold promiſe any thing, but as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſayth, would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme nothing. This <hi>Antigonus</hi> left more heires be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him in Courts and in Countreyes.</p>
               <p>And there was another <hi>Antigonus,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Euarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> for that he was a beneficiall Prince &amp; a benefactor in all Greece, and therfore his Statue was carried at A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens in the Banner of <hi>Peplon,</hi> with the Statues of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> in memorie of his benefits to the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians. Such is the continuance of a good Prince for vertues ſake, and the decay of euyll Princes for their wickednes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyrus,</hi> being relieued of the rude and barbarous nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <note place="margin">Diodor. lib. 17.</note> called <hi>Arimaſpi,</hi> being in much want and great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremytie of victualles, for their friendſhip &amp; liberality, cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged the name of <hi>Arimaſpi,</hi> &amp; called them <hi>Euargetes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Among many Emperours of Rome, called <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nines,</hi> one onely <hi>Antoninus,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Pius,</hi> for his zeale and loue towards his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, in baniſhing of Vſury, &amp; puniſhing Vſurers in Rome: one <hi>Alexander,</hi> called
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:9175:17"/>
                  <hi>Seuerus,</hi> for his vertuous ſeuerity. The reſt, as <hi>Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabalus, Comodus, Caracalla</hi> &amp; others, were rather Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, then good Emperours.</p>
               <p>So much might bee ſpoken of the kings of Egypt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <note place="margin">Many Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomies in Egypt.</note> ſo many <hi>Ptolomies,</hi> fewe good, ſauing <hi>Ptolo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Euargetes,</hi> a benefactor to his countrey, and <hi>Ptol. Philodelphos,</hi> for his ſingular loue &amp; zeale to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, in prouiding the Bible to bee tranſlated from He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew to Greek: yet had the other kings of Egypt, of ſuch louing names, one ſurnamed <hi>Ptol. Philopater,</hi> another <hi>Philometor,</hi> as though they ſhould reuerence and loue their parents, when in trueth, they were no otherwiſe but paracides and murtherers of their parents, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers of their Countreyes.</p>
               <p>The old kings of Egypt, which were in nomber 330. were called <hi>Pharaones,</hi> whoſe names, <hi>Herodot</hi> doth not recite, becauſe they were all called <hi>Pharaones,</hi> which in the Egyptian tongue, are called kings, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Mineus</hi> time that builded Memphis, vntil <hi>Salomons</hi> time: for his father in lawe was the laſt <hi>Pharao</hi> in Egypt.</p>
               <p>Then reigned <hi>Nicaule,</hi> the Q. of Egypt and Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia, <note place="margin">Ioſeph. lib. 8. cap. 2. How long the name of Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued.</note> who came to Ieruſalem to heare &amp; to ſee <hi>Salomon,</hi> with Camelles laden with gold, ſiluer and precious ſtones. After this Queene, the name of <hi>Pharaoes</hi> ended; which had continued 1300. yeres, from the firſt vnto the laſt, whoſe daughter, <hi>Salomon</hi> maried.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>Sectio. 5.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Naxarchus,</hi> the Philoſopher, flattered <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>axarchus.</note> the great, when he ſaw him make much mourning for <hi>Clytus,</hi> whom in his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:9175:18"/>
fury he ſlue. Art thou ignorant, <hi>Alexander,</hi> ſaid <hi>Anax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archus,</hi> that ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wiſe men haue placed the Image of Iuſtice hard by <hi>Iupiter,</hi> that whatſoeuer <hi>Iupiter</hi> doeth, that Iuſtice doeth alwayes allowe? A ſmall matter for <note place="margin">Diodor. lib. 17. Gel. lib. 3. cap. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, to kil <hi>Clitus, Parmenio,</hi> and <hi>Philotas</hi> his ſonne; when other meaner men then <hi>Alexander,</hi> do practiſe their policy, not onely to kill, but alſo to poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon kings &amp; princes: ſo was <hi>Alexander,</hi> that killed ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kings &amp; princes, poyſoned by his ſeruant <hi>Caſſander.</hi> So ſhould <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> haue bin, by his Phiſicion &amp; ſeruant <hi>Timochares,</hi> who offered <hi>Fabritius</hi> to poyſon <hi>Pirrhus,</hi> if <hi>Fabritius</hi> would. But the Romane Conſull ſent word to <hi>Pirrhus, Vrbem noſtram a filio</hi> Martis <hi>conditam, non ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenis,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cic. 3. Offic.</note> 
                  <hi>ſed armis bellum gerere:</hi> That Rome was builded by <hi>Mars</hi> his ſonne, to wat with weapons, and not with poyſon; concealing the name of <hi>Timochares,</hi> and yet warned <hi>Pirrhus</hi> to looke better to himſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antiochus</hi> the great had a Paraſite in court, named <hi>Minio,</hi> who flattering <hi>Antiochus,</hi> as <hi>Anaxarchus</hi> did <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> counſelled him to moue warres againſt the Romanes, as <hi>Hanibal</hi> did before him, whereby he loſt the name of <hi>Antiochus</hi> the great, in Aſia and in Syria, <note place="margin">Antiochus the great.</note> and was driuen by the Romanes, to liue within the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct of mount Taurus: ſo that the Romane <hi>Scipio</hi> wan Aſia fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Antiochus,</hi> and was named <hi>Scipio Aſiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> and not <hi>Magnus:</hi> for the Romanes could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the name of <hi>Magnus:</hi> So that by following of ill cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel, <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Great loſt his Greatneſſe in Aſia: and <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great loſt his life in Babylon.</p>
               <p>The like is hiſtoried of one <hi>Alexander Acarnan,</hi> that contrarywiſe, neuer tooke counſell to take warres in hand, for that he neuer doubted of the victory, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9175:18"/>
where &amp; how he might haue money, by practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of policy.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Liui. 33.</note>Many do imitate this raſh felow, who to accompliſh their trecherous purpoſe, make more haſte then good  ſpeed, without regard of that which doth follow: for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes are dangerous for ſeditious men to practiſe Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. <hi>Malum naſcens, facile opprimitur.</hi> Rebelles may not delay as <hi>Fab. Maximus</hi> did to weary <hi>Hanibal.</hi> Sedition is <note place="margin">Tacit. 11.</note> full of feare, one fearing another, leſt the one bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed by the other: all the practiſes of the ſeditious is to ſowe Diſcord, no hope reſteth vnto them, but by diſcord: and therefore ſaid <hi>Cicero</hi> againſt that ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Romane <hi>Cateline, Qui honores quieta Repub. deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, perturbata ſe conſequi poſſe arbitrantur.</hi> Many <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines</hi> were in Rome, which, vnder pretence of liberty, practiſed all the policyes they could, to ouerthrow the Commonwealth: <hi>Tumultum ex tumultu, et bellum ex bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo ſerunt.</hi> Neuer quiet, vntil they ſee the ſtate of a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vnquiet: and many ſay in their hearts, as <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line</hi> ſpake of Rome, <hi>Aut incendio aut ruina extinguam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Attilius Regulus</hi> was a man of great credit and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and of more truth and fayth towards his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, <note place="margin">Front. lib. 4. cap. 3.</note> then <hi>Cateline:</hi> hauing runne ouer ſo many great Offices in Rome and out of Rome, that at his death he wrote nothing to the Senators, but <hi>de Succeſſore,</hi> of a Succeſſor, which was hard for the Senators to find in Rome, the like to ſucceed him. So iuſt and faythfull a man was <hi>Attilius</hi> found in Rome.</p>
               <p>The like is hiſtoried of <hi>Luc. Mummius,</hi> after he had ſubdued many townes and Cities; but eſpecially Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthus, <note place="margin">Luc. Mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius.</note> the richeſt and chiefeſt City in all Greece, that he filled all Italy with Tablets, Statues, and Images, &amp;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:9175:19"/>
all other rich ornaments: and though <hi>Mummius</hi> might haue bin Lord of Corinthus, yet had he rather dye a poore man in his countrey at Rome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Attalus,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Philometor,</hi> had great delight to plant venemous hearbs, as Hemlocke, Wolfeband, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leborum, &amp; others: and being required of one of his Nobles, why he planted ſuch venemous hearbs, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, To practiſe policy.</p>
               <p>Such policy practiſed <hi>Dalila</hi> againſt <hi>Samſon: Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoes</hi> daughter againſt <hi>Salomon:</hi> &amp; <hi>Tullia, Tarquins</hi> wife <note place="margin">Iudg. 14. 3. Reg. 11.</note> practiſed ſuch policy againſt the king <hi>Seruius Tullus,</hi> her father. Some plow with <hi>Samſons</hi> heyfar, to their owne ouerthrow: and ſome with <hi>Minoes</hi> Cowe, to breed many monſtrous Minotaures, to deuoure their country. And too many plow againſt the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> with an Oxe and an Aſſe; and all this to practiſe policy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>Sectio 6.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N Greece were two generall facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Doreans, and Ionians: the Lacedemonians tooke part with the Doreans; and the Athenians, with the Ionians. From theſe two Factions <note place="margin">Two gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall factio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in Greece.</note> grew in Greece, ſuch ſeditions, that the Boetians, the Argiues, Elians, Mantineans, and others, ſome affecting the Doreans with the Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians, ſome affecting the Ionians with the Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that it brake out into ciuil warres, which continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 27. yeres, to the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Empire of Greece, which ſomtyme gaue ſo many ouerthrowes to the Perſians, ſo many victories at Maratho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at Artimeſium,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9175:19"/>
at Salamina, &amp; other-where, that now, by meanes of their factions &amp; ſeditions, <hi>Philip</hi> of Macedon ſaw ſuch oportunity to ſubdue the Graecians, which hee long thirſted for, that he ouercame Greece with Greekes; for ſo it is written, <hi>Graeci Graecorum manibus mactabantur,</hi> by meanes chiefly of their ciuil ſeditions and factions: he wan more townes in Greece by Greeks, then by the Macedonians.</p>
               <p>The like of the ciuill warres among the Romanes: the Danes thought it the fitteſt time to winne Rome <note place="margin">Front. lib. 1. cap. 10 Scorylo.</note> in ſuch a ſeditious time, as <hi>Philip</hi> did Greece: yet <hi>Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rylo</hi> their Generall at that time appoynted, doubting much of this enterpriſe, cauſed two great maſtiue dogs to fight eagerly before the people, that both were wel wearied: then <hi>Scorylo</hi> brought in a Wolfe in the ſight of theſe maſtiue dogs, &amp; ſtraight wayes both the dogs left off fighting, &amp; both of them ran fiercely, &amp; fought egerly with the Wolfe. The fierce ciuill warres and fighting of the Romanes at home, ſayd <hi>Scorylo,</hi> will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo do, when they ſee a Wolfe, I meane, a forrayne enemy, to commence warre againſt them.</p>
               <p>There was alſo in Athens, two factions, <hi>Pericles</hi> being the authour of one, and <hi>Cymon,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciades</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Two facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</note> the other. <hi>Pericles</hi> affected the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people; and <hi>Cimon</hi> preferred the Nobility, and fauoured their proceedings, in ſuch ſort, that Athens was neuer quiet, but when it was diſquieted with it ſelfe by meanes of factions, which do nouriſh ſeditions, hauing their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie-brayned Oratours to force the Athenians to fight with their tongues, <hi>conſilio, calamis, &amp; linguâ:</hi> for it was <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. Ariſtoph.</note> the diſpoſition of that City, neuer to conſult, as <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes</hi> ſayd, but too late: euery towne in Greece, was
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:9175:20"/>
ſo factious, that the glory of Greece, by meanes of factions and ſeditions, continued but 50. yeeres, and ſome odde in any greatneſſe.</p>
               <p>And in Sparta, for all <hi>Lycurgus</hi> care, and his lawes, he could not free Sparta from factions; and yet he deuided <note place="margin">Two facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Spartae. Obas and Philas.</note> them all into 2. factions, whom <hi>Lycurgus</hi> himſelfe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Obas</hi> &amp; <hi>Philas:</hi> which lawes &amp; decrees of <hi>Lycurgus</hi> were ſo kept for 500. yeres without violating them, for none in Greece durſt breake <hi>Lycurgus</hi> lawes, but <hi>Age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilaus,</hi> and that but once vpon great neceſſity, to puniſh ſeditions.</p>
               <p>In Carthage alſo they had two factions, the one fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion followed <hi>Hamilcar, Hanibals</hi> father, and after him his ſon <hi>Hanibals</hi> the other followed <hi>Hanno</hi> &amp; his frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds: ſo that in kingdoms and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries, factious men moued ſuch ſedition, wherby no greater harmes happened to kingdomes and countries, then by practiſing ſeditions and factions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hamilcar, Hannibals</hi> father ſo hated the Romans, that hauing 4. young youthes to his ſonnes, ſayd, that hee would haue 4. Lion whelps nouriſhed &amp; brought vp with his 4. ſonnes, as mortall enemies to the Romanes; and ſware <hi>Hannibal</hi> his eldeſt ſon, being of 9. yeres old, <note place="margin">Polib. 2.</note> to continue an enemy to the Romanes during his life: and further, to ſhew his malice &amp; enuy towards the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, he raiſed vp the duſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth with his foot, and ſaid, that then ſhould be the end of the warres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Rome &amp; Carthage, when one of both thoſe Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhould be brought to nothing but ſuch duſt.</p>
               <p>In Rome, before <hi>Fab. Max.</hi> time, they had but foure <note place="margin">Foure fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Rome.</note> factions, which were deuided by <hi>Tullus Hoſtilius</hi> the third king of Rome, and by him named <hi>Palatina, Coli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:9175:20"/>
Exquilina,</hi> and <hi>Suburrana,</hi> after the name of the foure gates of Rome, at that time being the Infancy of Rome: But after, it grew from foure factions to be fiue and thirty Tribes, that euery Tribe was full of diuers factions, and the Romane Empire waxed ſo mighty, that <hi>Fabius Maximus,</hi> when he was Cenſor in Rome, for that he brought all forraine factions within Rome, to be one of theſe foure, which <hi>Seruius Tullus</hi> named <note place="margin">Fab. na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Max.</note> 
                  <hi>Vrbanas factiones,</hi> was ſo gratefull to the Citizens of Rome, that they named him <hi>Fabius Maximus,</hi> which was the firſt time that he was called <hi>Maximus,</hi> for abridging the multitude of factions, that then would haue growen in Rome, vnto infinite numbers, if <hi>Fabius</hi> had not brought them vnder one of theſe foure.</p>
               <p>But in the time of <hi>Sylla</hi> and <hi>Marius,</hi> factions began ſo to multiply in Rome, as it did in Greece, that likewiſe <note place="margin">The ciuill wartes of the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</note> it brake out into ciuill warres, which continued from <hi>Sillaes</hi> time, vnto the laſt ouerthrow of <hi>Mar. Antonius,</hi> welnigh fourty yeeres, to the deſtruction of the whole Empire, ſome following the fury of <hi>Marius,</hi> as <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torius, Cynna, Carbo:</hi> and others followers of <hi>Sylla,</hi> as <hi>Metellus, Pompey,</hi> and others, that none might dwell in Rome, but thoſe that eyther ſhould bee on <hi>Marius</hi> ſide, or on <hi>Syllaes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus was the Empire deuided by factions, from <hi>Sylla</hi> to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> from <hi>Caeſar</hi> to <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> ſometime run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from <hi>Caeſar</hi> to <hi>Pompey,</hi> and from <hi>Pompey</hi> to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> vntill they and their factions were ſlayn by the ſword, and their countrey welnigh deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>Of all miſeries, ciuill warres is moſt miſerable, and a very Ocean ſea of all miſeries, in which, <hi>Nobilitas cum plebe perit,</hi> wherof <hi>Homer</hi> exclaimed, &amp; ſaid, Let him be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:9175:21"/>
curſed as an vnnatural monſter &amp; no man, that ſeeketh <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c. Iliad. 1. Cic. Phil. 12.</note> his countries harme. And <hi>Cicero</hi> in like ſort cryed out vpon him, <hi>Quem caedes ciuium, quem bellum ciuile delectat,</hi> and wiſhed ſuch to be caſt out of the ſociety of men, and to weed them out of the bounds of nature.</p>
               <p>Factions among great men, are more dangerous &amp; hard to be quenched, for that theſe potentates draw the people and moue them, which are compared to the ſea vnmoueable, vntill a tempeſt riſe: and therfore <hi>Plato</hi> thought good to ioyne <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> ſurnamed the iuſt, for his iuſtice, trueth and conſtancy, with <hi>Themiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tocles,</hi> being haughty and ſomewhat ambitious. And <hi>Lycurgus</hi> much commended the policy of <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lycurgus.</note> to put <hi>Vliſses</hi> forward to clayme <hi>Achilles</hi> armour, as wel as <hi>Aiax,</hi> who iudged himſelfe moſt worthy, in reſpect of his valor, to be next <hi>Achilles,</hi> throughout al Greece. This diſcord was tempred by <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> by giuing <hi>Achilles</hi> armour to <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> that wiſe and politike men might be eſtemed as well for counſell, as valiant men for valour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> the Emperour, was written vnto by his deare friend <hi>Maecenas,</hi> that if hee would haue a quiet Empire, and his ſubiects to loue him, he ſhould cut off faction, the chiefe cauſe of ſedition, and that the name of factions, or any other new name, tending to moue quarrels and debate, might be quite excluded out of Rome. And ſo doth <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> exhort, that <hi>Magiſtratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um &amp; potentum contentiones,</hi> the beginning of brawles <note place="margin">Ariſt. pol. 5.</note> and contentions, ſhould be ſtayed and ſtopt by lawes: if not by lawes, by the ſword, <hi>Adulta ſeditio melioribus conſilijs flectetur,</hi> ſayth <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What ſlaughter came of the cynders and aſhes of <hi>Pompey</hi> the great, of <hi>Cato,</hi> of <hi>Scipio,</hi> and of others, to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:9175:21"/>
reuenge their death vpon <hi>Caeſar</hi> and his friends? What murther, what warre, was, to reuenge the murthering of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> vpon <hi>Brutus, Caſsius,</hi> and others? The Lawe of <hi>Thraſybulus,</hi> which curbed the thirty Tyrants in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, could doe no good in Rome, though <hi>Cicero</hi> did what he could, in perſwading <hi>Thraſybulus</hi> law to take <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> place with the people: For then euery man in Rome ſeemed as a Serpent one to another, ready in armes one to kill another. <hi>Oroſius</hi> hereupon induceth a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of <hi>Medea,</hi> of a Serpent ſlayne, of whoſe teeth ſet in <note place="margin">Oroſ. li. 6. cap. 17.</note> the ground by <hi>Medea,</hi> grew ſo many armed men, who preſently fought ſo within themſelues, that one deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed another. Such was the ſlaughter by the ciuill warres at Rome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>Sectio. 7.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heopompus</hi> being demaunded, why did Sparta flouriſh? Is it for that their kings gouerne their ſubiects wiſely, or that their ſubiects obey their kings faithfully? <hi>Theopompus</hi> anſwered, We practiſe in Sparta, but to indure labour <note place="margin">Theopom. ſaying of Sparta. No ſeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Sparta.</note> to ouercome our enemies, and to obey our kings, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer kings gouerne, the commaundement is giuen to ſubiects fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, to vſe their ſhield, &amp; not the ſword. The law in Sparta was therefore, that the ſouldier that loſt his ſhield in the field among the enemies, ſhould dye for it. The ſword is put into the hands of princes, to puniſh offendors, and to cut off diſobedient and ſeditious ſubiects. Chirurgians cut off rotten &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trified members, from the ſound members; which may
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9175:22"/>
be well likened to <hi>Gangraena,</hi> which muſt of neceſſity be cut off, leſt the whole body periſh. God vſed to ſhew ſuch ſeuerity to thoſe factious Rebells the Iewes, for their diſobedience, that fire came from heauen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue and burned them, and the earth belowe ſwallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vved them for their factious diſobedience, which of all other Nations were moſt factious to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, to <hi>Ioſua</hi> at Iericho, and from time to time, to the Iudges in Iſrael.</p>
               <p>It was euer the wonted practice of policy among the ſeditious and factious people, to taunt Magiſtrates, or to ſpeake ſome whiſpering ſpeech againſt a prince, to feele and to heare, who will ioyne with them to moue ſeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Theſe be the Vipers that bite men priuily: theſe be the domeſticall Serpents, the ſecret brue-bates of <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Commonwealths, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is no fayth found, nor othes to be beleeued, as <hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> ſayth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> hearing that a ſlaunderous fellow, one <hi>Elianus,</hi> ſpake vnreuerent words of the Emperour, the Magiſtrates willing to puniſh him; <hi>Auguſtus</hi> commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <note place="margin">Suet. in Aug.</note> thoſe that accuſed him, to goe and tell <hi>Elianus, Sciat Elianus, Auguſtum habere linguam,</hi> that <hi>Auguſtus</hi> had alſo a tongue, both to puniſh and to pardon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip</hi> of Macedon, in like ſort to his friends that perſwaded him to baniſh the like lewd fellowes, for their ſpeach, out of his court and countrey, ſayd, God <note place="margin">Plut. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheg.</note> forbid, leſt they ſhould ſpeake of mee more in another Country then in Macedonia. But theſe were dilatory plees to looke further vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to find more fellowes of the like practice.</p>
               <p>The example of <hi>Raymerus</hi> is much more commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which looked vnto the diſpoſition of his Noble men, and ſaw them vntractable, little waying the care
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:9175:22"/>
and loue the king had vnto them, contemning &amp; deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing both him and his lawes, giuing eare to ſeditious men, vntill the king ſaw their practice, waxed angry, perceiuing that they eſteemed him not as their king, cauſed 11. of theſe, whom he ſaw moſt contentious, to <note place="margin">Lipſ. lib. 3</note> be put to the ſword in the City of Oſca, giuing them this taunt withall, <hi>Neſcit Vulpecula cum quo ludat.</hi> A ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat, not to pluck haires from Lions, as the prouerb is, <hi>Lecnem vellicare.</hi> To ſerue a king, ſaith <hi>Braſidas,</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in three precepts: <hi>Velle, obedire, &amp; vereri.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Braſida<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> precepts.</note>
               </p>
               <p>A certayne king in Perſia, vſed in like ſort as <hi>Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merus</hi> did in Spayne, but of meaner perſons, which for ſome reprochfull taunting wordes, that they ſpake of the king, he cauſed thoſe ſcoffers noſtrils, quite on both ſides to be cut off, ſaying, <hi>Ecce ſigillum Regis in conuitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores,</hi> Behold the kings ſeale againſt ſcoffers. This ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is more commended in theſe princes, then the cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency of <hi>Philip</hi> or of <hi>Auguſtus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What became of the taunt which the Egyptia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s gaue to <hi>Ochus</hi> K. of Perſia, naming the K. the Aſſe of Perſia? <note place="margin">King O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus taunt to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians.</note> ſaid <hi>Ochus, Faciam vt hic aſinus veſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bouem depaſcat.</hi> I wil make the Aſſe of Perſia eate your Oxe of Egypt: for the Egyptians worſhipped an Oxe, which they called <hi>Apis,</hi> as one of their chiefe gods, which within a while after, <hi>Ochus,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> marched with a great <note place="margin">Oroſ. li. 3. cap. 7.</note> army and ſubdued Egypt, and ſacrificed their Oxe and their god <hi>Apis,</hi> according to his promiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cotis,</hi> a Thracian K. anſwered one, that ſaid his ſeuere gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was rather fury then clemency towards his <note place="margin">Cotis.</note> ſubiects. Yea, ſaid <hi>Cotis, hic furor meus ſanos reddit ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tós.</hi> Clemency muſt be ioyned with ſeuerity. This my ſeuerity, ſaid <hi>Cotis,</hi> ſhall make my ſubiects both to loue me and to feare me: <hi>Nimia clementia nocet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:9175:23"/>
Had <hi>Artabanus</hi> obſerued the rule of <hi>Raymerus,</hi> or the ſeuerity of <hi>Cotis,</hi> he needed not to haue fled ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Artaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> from Parthia to king <hi>Izetes,</hi> beyond Armenia, a far meaner king then himſelfe; neither to feare the ſnares and trappes of his ſubiects, being ſo great a king, called the king of kings; for ſo the kings of Parthia are called; but hee was reſtored to his kingdome, by this meane king <hi>Izetes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A thouſand miſhaps may happen to princes, which ſubiects are free of. Examples may be found of <hi>Iugurth</hi> king of Numidia, and of <hi>Perſius,</hi> king of Perſia, who were taken Captiues in their owne kingdomes, and dyed priſoners in Rome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>ſapiens,</hi> the French king, ſaw the king his father taken captiue in his owne kingdome, and caried into England; and the whole kingdome of Fraunce poſſeſt of Engliſhmen.</p>
               <p>The Romane Hiſtories are full of theſe horrible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, that by ſeditions and factions, the whole Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire was welnigh deſtroyed, that I need not declare of <hi>Tomoembeus,</hi> the great Soldan of Egypt and Affricke, king and Lord of ſo many Nations, in his owne king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <note place="margin">Tomoem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beus. Lip. lib. 2.</note> how cruelly and ſtrangely he was both depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of his kingdome and of his life: And how the great king, <hi>de nouo orbe, Mexicanus,</hi> after infinite good <note place="margin">Mexicanus</note> ſucceſſe of great fame and fortune, loſt ſuddenly both fame and fortune.</p>
               <p>I need not confirme theſe hiſtories with authority, as of <hi>Achab, Zedechias,</hi> &amp; other, who felt the iuſt Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God; neyther of <hi>Manaſſes</hi> and <hi>Nabuchadnezar,</hi> one <note place="margin">2. Reg. 10</note> confeſſing the Lord to bee God, being a king among beaſtes; the other a captiue and a priſoner out of his
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:9175:23"/>
owne kingdome, of whom the Greeke Prouerbe is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Miſery, captiuity and want, make kings to know the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. It is a true ſaying, <hi>Miſeria bona mater prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> would know of his friend <hi>Aſinius Pollio,</hi> if he would come with him to the battell of <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> betweene <hi>Mar. Antonius</hi> and him. He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Emperour, In ciuil warre I wil take no part, but <note place="margin">Vell. 11.</note> I will reſt and be a pray to the Conquerour. <hi>Tit. At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus,</hi> though <hi>Pompey</hi> by a Decree pronounced him a Rebel that would forſake his Senators, the Conſuls and the ſtate of the Common-wealth in ſo troubleſome a time, yet <hi>Atticus</hi> was of the like opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as <hi>Q. Hortenſius</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hortenſius ſaying.</note> was, who often vſed to brag that he had neuer byn in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ciuill warres. <hi>Cicero</hi> wrote his Epiſtle to them being his deere frends, that ſcattered cattel wil come to their flocke: how much more ſhould ſuch wiſe men be a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort <note place="margin">Cic. ad Att.</note> to their afflicted countrey and follow the beſt ſort, ſeing <hi>Cato</hi> himſelfe, <hi>Viua virtutis Imago,</hi> was a Captaine in theſe warres.</p>
               <p>Obſerue the nature of factions in the beſt men. <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Cato</hi> went out of Rome, as men determyned and reſolute to take part with the beſt men, and with the ſtate of the Empyre to abide what ſo euer came of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pomp. Atticus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Q. Hortenſius,</hi> men of no leſſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and credit in Rome then they were, forſooke to be factious or to take part with eyther <hi>Pompey</hi> or <hi>Caeſar:</hi> at that time ſpake <hi>Cato</hi> to <hi>Pompey</hi> to ſtrike the ground according to his promiſe, yet <hi>Solon</hi> in Athens, decreed a law, that they which would be neuters in ciuil warres, <note place="margin">Gel. li. 11. cap. 12.</note> and ſeperate themſelues in their Countries calamities, they ſhould be baniſhed <hi>igne &amp; aqua.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prophet <hi>Elizeus</hi> ſpake to <hi>Ioas</hi> king of Iſrael being
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:9175:24"/>
in ſuch diſtreſſe as Rome was, and bade <hi>Ioas</hi> ſmite the ground with his foot: and <hi>Ioas</hi> ſmote the ground three times and ceaſed. <hi>Elizeus</hi> was angry and ſayd, Thou ſhouldeſt haue ſmitten fiue, ſixe, or ſeuen times, and ſo <note place="margin">4. Reg. 13.</note> many victories ſhouldeſt thou haue had ouer the Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, as thou ſtrookeſt the ground.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Pompey</hi> alſo ſayd to <hi>Cato,</hi> If he ſhould but ſtrike the ground of Italy with his foot, hee ſhould want no men <note place="margin">Plut. in Pomp.</note> on his ſide to fight againſt <hi>Caeſar:</hi> But <hi>Pompey</hi> could not keepe promiſe with <hi>Cato,</hi> as <hi>Elizeus</hi> did with <hi>Ioas.</hi> Many promiſe more then they can performe, and doe deceiue themſelues and others.</p>
               <p>I could well compare theſe ſeditious people to <hi>Balaam,</hi> who being ſent for by king <hi>Balac,</hi> promiſing him great rewardes to come and curſe Iſrael: as <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> rode on his iorney, an Angel with a drawen ſword in his hand ſtood in his way, which the Aſſe ſawe and ſtarted, but <hi>Balaam</hi> ſawe not the Angell, vntill his Aſſe ſpake to him, and aſked <hi>Balaam</hi> why he ſtrake him?</p>
               <p>Theſe Aſſes cary ſome falſe <hi>Balaam</hi> or other, not on their backs, but in their bellyes, that had rather go with <hi>Balaam</hi> to <hi>Balak</hi> to curſe Iſrael, and to conſpire againſt their owne natiue countrey, and if they can not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile <note place="margin">Num. 22.</note> by curſing &amp; banning, they will practiſe another way by policy and counſell, as <hi>Balaam</hi> did to deceiue Iſrael.</p>
               <p>But theſe practiſers doe as <hi>Benhadad</hi> did, when hee was ouerthrowen in the mountaines, he ſaid, that the <note place="margin">The blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy of Benhadad. 3. Reg. 20.</note> Gods of the mountaynes were againſt him, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Benhadad</hi> would haue a battell in the Valley with the Iſraelites: ſo theſe <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſes euer haue done and will do, if they faile of their practice in the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:9175:24"/>
they wil practize in the valley: if they fayle in the valley, they will practiſe their policy in Kings Courts.</p>
               <p>Rebelles haue their ſnares layd downe, how trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may be wrought, and their places appointed where their treaſon may be performed, and their time when to execute their treaſon: So did <hi>Pauſanias</hi> kill <hi>Philip</hi> of <note place="margin">Pauſanias. Chaerea.</note> Macedon at a Marriage: So did <hi>Chaerea</hi> kill <hi>Claudius</hi> the Emperour going to the Theaters: So did the fryer of Fraunce murther the King at his confeſſion. What dare not practiſers of policy do, if they dare kill Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Kings and princes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Claudius Nero</hi> ſound no better way to feare <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> his great enemy, then to throw <hi>Haſdrubals</hi> head in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Tent of his brother <hi>Hannibal,</hi> which ſo amazed <hi>Hannibal</hi> and his army, that they made haſte from Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage to Italy.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Hanibal</hi> had nothing to comfort him, but to nippe the Romanes of ſo many heads of Senators, of Conſuls, of Praetors, and of Romane Magiſtrates at the battell of Canna, of Trebeia, and of Thraſimena, that requited his brothers head. But theſe nippes were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Hanibal</hi> and <hi>Scipio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For it was <hi>Sillaes</hi> practice, to put Italy in fright, and to make Rome amazed at his tyranny againſt his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, that <hi>Cato</hi> wondred much to ſee ſo many heads of Magiſtrates and of Roman Citizens vpon poles, hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">Plut. in Caton. Oroſ. li. 5. cap. 21.</note> on euery gate at Rome, about the Capitoll, and in the market place, and that no Romane for Romes ſake, had killed <hi>Silla.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Golias</hi> head was caried by <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Saul,</hi> the Philiſtines fled, and they were followed vnto Geth, and vnto Acaron, and the ſlaughter was
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:9175:25"/>
great of the Philiſtians, and their terrour was more to ſee their Captaine <hi>Golias</hi> without a head, and therefore was the Sword of <hi>Golias</hi> hanged in the Temple at Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a Trophey of victorie, as the picture of the Sun <note place="margin">1. Reg. 17</note> was vpon <hi>Ioſhuas</hi> Tombe for his victory at Gibeon.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Holophernes</hi> head was brought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the campe to Bethulia, by <hi>Iudyth,</hi> a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the ſlaughter was great of the Aſſyrians, and much more were they aſtoniſhed <note place="margin">Inaith 14</note> and aſhamed, to find their General <hi>Holophernes</hi> without a head, and that by a woman.</p>
               <p>It was great policy in <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund all his ſouldiers to ſhoote their pieces and their arrowes together toward king <hi>Perus,</hi> in India, percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <note place="margin">Ore. lib. 3. cap. 19. Dioder. lib. 17.</note> that the ſoldiers would fly if the king were ſlaine. And therefore diuers great Captaines did practiſe ſuch policy afterward to their ſoldiers: as <hi>Leuinus</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul perſwaded his ſouldiers, and ſhewed them a naked bloudy ſword in his hand, ſaying, that hee had killed <hi>Pirrhus.</hi> The like policy practiſed <hi>Iugurth,</hi> ſaying to his Numidian ſoldiers, that hee had ſlayne <hi>Caius Marius</hi> with his owne hand.</p>
               <p>It is the onely marke, that euery trecherous ſoldier in the field, and euery ſeditious ſubiect in the country ſhoot at, I meane, the head: for if the head be off, the body muſt needs fall. Theſe be the very home-Vipers and ſecret Serpents that deuoure their natiue ſoyle.</p>
               <p>Theſe practiſing Vipers are often troubled with the like monſtrous Image which <hi>Hanibal</hi> ſaw &amp; was aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in his dreame, &amp; asking what he was, the Image <note place="margin">Cic. de diuinat. 1.</note> ſaid: <hi>Vaſtitas Italiae.</hi> Theſe Vipers ſee nothing waking nor ſleeping, but the image of <hi>Hanibal, vaſtitatem patria,</hi> the ſpoyle of their countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:9175:25"/>
               <head>Sectio. 8.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heophraſtus</hi> the Philoſopher, and the ſucceſſour of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his maſter, in Athens, faith, that the playing vpon a Harp, Lute, or any other inſtrument, doth heale the biting of ſome Vipers; <note place="margin">Alex. lib. 2. cap. 17.</note> which <hi>Aſclepiades</hi> the Phiſician doth confirme, that frantike people that are not well ſettled in their wittes, can by no meanes better recouer their health, <hi>quàm ſymphonia &amp; vocum conſenſu,</hi> then by the conſent of harmony and the voyce of a man: for <hi>Iſme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> the Theban healed many Boetians his country me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that were troubled with phrenſie and madneſſe, with ſymphony and harmony of muſike.</p>
               <p>It is to bee beleeued, that <hi>Iſmenias</hi> with his Flute could eaſe the Boetians, and <hi>Aſclepiades</hi> with his phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſike heale the frantike. Such practiſes were neceſſary to be in many places, to preuent lunatike policies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> with his Harpe did often mitigate the fury of king <hi>Saul,</hi> &amp; aſſwaged oftentimes the phrenetical ſpirit <note place="margin">4. Reg. ca. 3.</note> of <hi>Saul.</hi> Againe, <hi>Elizeus,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> K. of Iuda, and <hi>Ieboram</hi> king of Iſrael, would know the euent of the warres betweene them and <hi>Meſa,</hi> king of Moab, <hi>Elizeus</hi> called for a Minſtrel, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Minſtrel plaid, the hand of the Lord came vpon <hi>Elizeus,</hi> and then he told the kings of the victory they ſhould haue ouer Moab.</p>
               <p>Harmony, ſaith <hi>Cicero,</hi> doth <hi>incitare languentes, et lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guefacere</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cic. de leg. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>excitates,</hi> nothing quickneth mans mind more the ſuch muſike: &amp; I doubt, ſuch frantik men be likewiſe in many places abroad, ready like <hi>Saul</hi> with their ſpeares
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:9175:26"/>
in their hands, that neyther <hi>Dauid</hi> with his Harpe, nor <hi>Elizeus</hi> with his Minſtreles can heale theſe men of their frenzy.</p>
               <p>Theſe be the Vipers that ſting their friendes worſe in England, then <hi>Hanibals</hi> Vipers ſtinged the Romans their enemies in Italy.</p>
               <p>Theſe Vipers are ſo ful of poyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that if they might kill with their ſight, like the Cockatrice: or if they might infect with their breath, as the Viper of Affricke doth; and as they ſay of ſome kind of wolues, which if they come within their breath, they would kill ſome men both with ſight and breath. And therefore we haue a Caueat to take heed of ſuch infected wolues that haue daungerous and ſtinking breath, and be in ſheepes clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which liue as wolues, &amp; dye as ſwine, they liue in all common-wealths, &amp; they dwel together in cities, in towns, and in houſes: we muſt be as ſubtill as Serpents againſt Serpents.</p>
               <p>Yet the Egiptians think themſelues moſt happy and fortunate, and in great fauour with their gods, when <note place="margin">The ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition of Egypt.</note> they are bitten with Serpents, Vipers and Crocadiles, becauſe they worſhip thoſe kind of Serpents as their gods; and truly fit gods for ſuch a ſuperſtitious nation, for that they worſhipped no other gods, but Serpents and beaſts: wherein they were reprehended of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Grecians: for you ſhall not read, that Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadiles, <note place="margin">Cic. lib. 1. de Natur.</note> Cats, and Dogs, and for that Wolues are like Dogs, and ſuch other like, were ſlayn or kild in Egypt; for they haue ſuch beaſts in reuerence, and worſhip them as gods.</p>
               <p>So ſuperſtitious were they in Egypt, that it was cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an abomination among them to eate with the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes: <note place="margin">Can. 43.</note>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:9175:26"/>
for the nature of ſuperſtition is, to condemne all other men in reſpect of themſelues. So <hi>Ioſeph</hi> vſed the Hebrewes his brethren by themſelues.</p>
               <p>So did the Samaritans hate the Iewes, that they might not eate or conuerſe with the lewes: for ſo did the woman of Samaria take vp Chriſt at <hi>Iacobs</hi> Well, <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.</note> hee being a Iewe, to aske water at a Samaritans hand: but wee haue Iewes, and Samaritans, Hebrues, and Egyptians, ſo mingled, that wee know not one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
               <p>What will not blinde ſuperſtition cauſe to doo?</p>
               <p>It made <hi>Nabuchadnezar</hi> and all Babel to ſay and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe: Great art thou God Bel. <note place="margin">Dar. 14.</note>
               </p>
               <p>It made the Epheſians ſay: Great art thou <hi>Diana</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Epheſians. <note place="margin">Acts. 19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>It made <hi>Charles</hi> the ſe uenth, the French king, with the conſent of all his Counſell, to beleeue the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious ſpeech of <hi>Ioanna Lotharinga,</hi> a woman, that ſhee was ſent from God, to driue the Engliſhmen <note place="margin">Ioſeph. lib. 18. cap. 4</note> out of Fraunce, in the great Warres betweene Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Fraunce. It is thus hiſtoried, <hi>Arma gerebat, viris preibat:</hi> But ſhee was taken by Engliſhmen, and burned at Rhotomagium.</p>
               <p>It made <hi>Pallina,</hi> the onely fayreſt and chaſte Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman of Rome, to refuſe two hundred thouſand Drachmes of <hi>Decius Mundus,</hi> a yong Romane knight, for one nights lodging, and yet ſhee came moſt ioyfully with the conſent of all her friendes and of her husband <hi>Saturninus,</hi> to lye with God <hi>Anubis</hi> in the Temple of <hi>Iſis,</hi> for nothing, by the meanes of <hi>Iſis</hi> Prieſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:9175:27"/>
But this practize being found out by <hi>Pallina,</hi> ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playned to her huſband <hi>Saturninus,</hi> and her huſband to the Emperour <hi>Tiberius,</hi> who firſt cauſed the prieſts of <hi>Iſis</hi> to be ſlaine with the ſword, the Idoll of <hi>Iſis</hi> to be drownd in Tyber, the great God <hi>Anubis</hi> to be burned with fire, and <hi>Decius Mundus</hi> the yong knight for euer to bee baniſhed from Rome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nabuchadnezar</hi> deſtroyed the prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, as <hi>Tiberius</hi> deſtroyed the prieſts of <hi>Iſis</hi> in Rome: And ſo God ſtirred vp <hi>Iehu,</hi> to deſtroy the houſe of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab</hi> in Iſrael.</p>
               <p>All dangerous and rebellious ſeditions grow of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous ſuperſtition: therefore the Lord reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Ochoſia,</hi> becauſe he maried the daughter of <hi>Achab.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> was reprehended of the Prophet <hi>Elize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> &amp; in danger of his life, for that he ioyned in friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <note place="margin">4. Reg. 1.</note> with the ſame Idolatrous <hi>Achab.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Salomon,</hi> by growing in friendſhip with <hi>Pharaoes</hi> daughter, loſt his kingdome: and <hi>Sampſon,</hi> by marying <note place="margin">3. Reg. 11</note> with <hi>Dalila</hi> a Philiſtine, loſt his life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sara</hi> complayned vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> that <hi>Iſmael</hi> ſhould not be in one houſe with <hi>Iſaac</hi> her ſonne; which words though they were grieuous vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> yet God commaunded him to doe what <hi>Sara</hi> ſayd; for in <hi>Iſaac</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 21.</note> ſhall thy ſeed be bleſſed.</p>
               <p>We muſt not only auoyd euill mens company, but alſo depart from the place where they bee, and where they dwell. For God commaunded <hi>Abraham</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from Vt, his owne countrey, being an Idolatrous <note place="margin">Gen. 12.</note> place. So God commaunded <hi>Iacob</hi> to ſhun Meſopota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia <note place="margin">Gen. 31.</note> &amp; the company of his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> a wicked man.</p>
               <p>Whileſtany of the ſeditious houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> liued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:9175:27"/>
the Iewes, the plague neuer ceaſed in Iſrael: but when at the requeſt and petition of the Gibio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, <note place="margin">2. Sam. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> hanged them vp, the Plague ceaſed.</p>
               <p>The like is hiſtoryed of <hi>Phinees,</hi> that, for killing of <note place="margin">Numb. 25</note> 
                  <hi>Zymri</hi> and <hi>Coſbi</hi> for their whoredome in the camp, the Plague ceaſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elizeus</hi> being asked of <hi>Hazael</hi> why he wept? I weep, ſaid the Prophet, knowing the euill thou ſhalt do to the children of Iſrael, in burning their houſes and Cities, <note place="margin">4. Reg. 8.</note> ſlaying their yong men with the ſword, &amp; in that thou ſhalt daſh out the braines of their ſucking children, and all to teare their women with child.</p>
               <p>Such factious and ſeditious men, <hi>qui ex fraude, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laciis et mendaciis, &amp;c.</hi> as ſayth <hi>Cicero,</hi> haue diuers tymes the like intent, as <hi>Hazael</hi> had to Iſrael. A ſeditious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſeeketh miſchiefe in his heart. <note place="margin">Pro. 17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>There was a letter writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> climing for the Empire of Rome, raging in his fury againſt his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, willing him not to giue too much care to ſuch as are greedy ſeditious men, &amp; deſirous of ſlaughters, and neuer ſatisfied with bloud, who cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelled <hi>Caeſar</hi> to that purpoſe, that the City of Rome being taken, they might take rape and ſpoyle, and vſe their luſt for a Law.</p>
               <p>Againſt theſe &amp; ſuch like, the Prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> doth pronounce famyne, plague, warre &amp; deuouring beaſts, <note place="margin">Ezech. 7.</note> to try (if it be poſſible) whether ill and wicked people wil mend and become ſeruants to God, and ſubiects to their King: for (ſayth <hi>Salomon</hi> of ſuch men) if they had <note place="margin">Pro. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> called for knowledge, and ſought for wiſdome, as they ſought after money; or had they digged for celeſtial wiſdome, as they did for earthly treaſure: then ſhould they vnderſtand the feare of the Lord, and finde the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:9175:28"/>
knowledge of God: but ſuch ſeeke ſpoyles and prayes, they onely muſe how they might come by money, <hi>vita et ſanguis eorum pecunia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet <hi>Dioniſins,</hi> after hee had robbed the Temple of <hi>Proſerpina</hi> among the Locreſians, and robbed <hi>Iupiter Olympius</hi> of his golden Garment in Peloponeſus, and robbed <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> of his golden beard in Epidau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, <note place="margin">Cic. lib. 3. de Natur.</note> without any reſiſting of him, for that the people thought that he ſhould be puniſhed as <hi>Xerxes</hi> was once in Greece, that eyther <hi>Proſerpina</hi> would haue plucked out his eyes, or <hi>Iupiter</hi> would haue kild him with thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolts, or <hi>Eſculapius</hi> would haue tortured him with plagues and long ſickenes, ſuppoſing <hi>Dioniſius</hi> ſhould not haue ſo eſcaped free for his ſacriledge, no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Xerxes,</hi> who for burning their gods and their Temples in Greece, their gods haue ſo plagued him, that three hundred thouſand Perſians were ſlaine in Greece, and <note place="margin">Cic. de leg. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Xerxes</hi> himſelfe murthered by his Nephew <hi>Artabanus,</hi> and therfore went they to the Temple of <hi>Eumenides,</hi> which were <hi>Vltrices et vindices facinorum et ſcelerum,</hi> to yeeld thankes to theſe Furyes for the reuenging of the violating of their Temples, their Altars &amp; their gods.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>Sectio 9.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HEAGINES</hi> leading an Army a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Magarians, his army would know of him whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he would put them to martch in order of battell. <hi>Theagines</hi> anſwered, at Megara, and in the mean ſeaſon, ſent ſecretly certein Horſmen,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:9175:28"/>
like the enemyes to ſet vpon them on the ſodaine and to aſſault the Athenians: which being done, <hi>Theagines</hi> marked how euery ſouldier was forward &amp; took place to fight. I promiſed you, ſaid <hi>Theagines,</hi> this morning to put you in array at Megara; march now forward, and be as ready for the enemy at al times as now, and ſeeke not to know the ſecret purpoſe of your Captaine, but be ready at a becke: for as <hi>Clearchus</hi> the Lacedemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſaid: good Souldiers ought to be more carefull of their Captaine then of their enemies. Now <hi>Theagines</hi> did this, to finde out falſe and ſeditious Souldiers from the true.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Licinius Craſsus,</hi> being asked when he would remoue his Tents, anſwered: Doeſt thou meane to ſleepe, that thou wouldſt know whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they remoue? <hi>Vereris ne tubam</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Front. lib. 1. cap. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>exaudeas?</hi> So <hi>Metellus</hi> anſwered the like queſtion, being asked what he thought to do the next morning: I wold burne my Coate, ſayd <hi>Metellus,</hi> if I thought my Coate could tell it.</p>
               <p>How many thinke you are of <hi>Metellus</hi> mind, which would that none ſhould know their policy, neither the time of their practiſe? they will not onely burne their coates and their ſhyrts, but their ſkinnes and their fleſh, and yet often times their practiſes are deſcryed.</p>
               <p>In Egipt, ſuch ſeditious and trecherous men, for their ſecret practiſe, doe worſhip and alſo ſacrifice vnto the dumbe Image of <hi>Harpocrates,</hi> that all ſecret practiſes might be kept cloſe.</p>
               <p>In Rome they do ſacrifice vnto <hi>Angerona,</hi> whoſe finger is alwayes on her mouth, in token of ſilence.</p>
               <p>In Perſia, they offer alſo ſacrifice vnto that Image of ſilence, whoſe lippe is ſealed vp with a ſignet, with the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:9175:29"/>
which the Perſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vſe at the chuſing of any of the kings Counſell, to lay the kings ſignet on their lips. But to whom doe they ſacrifice their tongue? To the dumbe Deuill that ſtoppeth their tongues from praying vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">So did Alex. to Epheſtion.</note> God: and to the deafe Deuill they ſacrifice their eares, becauſe they will not heare the Word of God; for thereby ſhould their policy and practice bee knowne.</p>
               <p>The Romanes, to preuent theſe ſecret practiſers, brought vp Dogges, which are quicke of ſent, in high <note place="margin">Arneb. li. 6. aduerſ. gentes.</note> Towers, &amp; fed Geeſe in the Capitoll, which are quicke of hearing, that by the barking of the Dogges, warning might be giuen of the enemies comming, and by the gaggling of the geeſe, men might be waked out of their ſleepe, as <hi>Manlius</hi> was, to ſaue both Rome and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitoll from the Gaules. So did <hi>Maſiniſſa,</hi> king of Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midia, bind great dogges in his bed-chamber, to watch practiſers.</p>
               <p>But Chriſt gaue vs a better leſſon, and a ſounder watch, <hi>Vigilate &amp; orate,</hi> Watch and pray: the Deuill is that Dogge that commeth in through the windowe. Our Sentinel is our conſcience, which ſhould bee a brydle to curbe wicked men from trechery, from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and from conſpiracy.</p>
               <p>The ſeditious man, ſayth <hi>Cicero, Panam ſemper ante eculos verſari vidit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paulus Emilius</hi> commaunded his ſoldiers to be vnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in their watch, for that they ſhould not ſleepe, and be more carefull of their watch. <note place="margin">Xenoph, in Paed.</note>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>Cyrus</hi> would not haue his ſoldiers to be idle, leſt they ſhould become quarrellous and ſeditious.</p>
               <p>I may not omit a rare example, of <hi>Manlius</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:9175:29"/>
to correct his yong ſonne <hi>Manlius,</hi> who fought a battell againſt the enemies with good ſucceſſe of vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, yet againſt his fathers rule, and therfore was to be <note place="margin">Front. li. 4 cap. 1.</note> puniſhed with ſtripes, and by his father to be ſlaine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the military diſcipline, vntill the ſouldiers tooke part with young <hi>Manlius</hi> againſt the father. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition grew hereby in the eampe, that young <hi>Manlius,</hi> to auoyd this ſedition, made meanes to the army that he might be puniſhed, to ſatiſfy the law and his fathers commaundement.</p>
               <p>This was a rare example: but we ſpeake of ſuch as neither eſteemed parents nor Prince, neither King nor countrey: ſuch a one was <hi>Iudas Galilaeus,</hi> ſo ſeditious, <note place="margin">Iudea pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued by ſedition.</note> that he brought a multitude of the Iewes, like himſelf, to follow him, and promiſed them that the Romanes ſhould be by him fully vanquiſhed. But <hi>Felix</hi> the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Preſident made ready certayne Romane ſoldiers to ouerthrow them, and put them all to the ſword in the wildernes.</p>
               <p>Straight after this ouerthrow, another ſeditious prophet came from Egypt to Ieruſalem, profeſſing the name of a Prophet, promiſing the people, if they would follow him to mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Oliuet, fiue furlongs from the City, they ſhould ſee the walles of Ieruſalem, at his commaundement to fall downe, as the walles of Iericho did at the blowing of Rammes hornes, by the <note place="margin">Ioſh. 6.</note> commaundement of <hi>Ioſua,</hi> that thereby they might eaſily enter the City.</p>
               <p>Theſe were ſuch priuate ſeditious men, as <hi>Aton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> a Shepheard, and after him <hi>Barcoſbe,</hi> who kept the people in hand, and made the <hi>Rabbins</hi> themſelues to beleeue, that by his policy and practice, they would
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:9175:30"/>
make an end of the Romane warres.</p>
               <p>Thus from one ſeditious man to another, the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude was led like a Flocke of ſheepe to the ſlaughter, that when <hi>Feſtus</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Felix,</hi> he found all Iudaea full of ſuch Robbers, Cooſeners, Magicians, yea Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurers and deceyuers of the people, that <hi>Feſtus</hi> cut them off by degrees, as <hi>Felix</hi> did before <hi>Feſtus,</hi> who met with <note place="margin">Ioſeph. lib. 20. cap. 6.</note> this Egyptian and his fellowes, &amp; ſlew foure hundred and tooke foure hundred aliue, yet theſe being deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cut off, like Hydraes head they ſtill multiplyed: ſo ſeditious were the Iewes.</p>
               <p>In the time of <hi>Antiochus,</hi> many wicked men went out of Ieruſalem, and moued much people, ſaying:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eamus et diſponamus teſtamentum Gentibus:</hi> Let vs go &amp; make couenant with the Heathen. This practiſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the people well, ſo that at Ieruſalem was an open Schole of the Heathen, againſt whom <hi>Amos</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet cryed, <hi>Vae qui opulenti eſtis in Sion, et conſiditis in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Amos. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>montibus</hi> Samariae: Wo be vnto you which are rich in Sion, and truſt to the mountaines of Samaria: wo be vnto them that depart from Bethel to Bethauen, from God to the Deuill, from their friends to their foes.</p>
               <p>Another Magician named <hi>Theudas,</hi> profeſſed him ſelfe to be a Prophet, and for proofe therof willed the Iewes to follow him to Iordan, &amp; they ſhould ſee him do as much with a word at Iordan, as either <hi>Elizeus</hi> did with <hi>Elias</hi> mantle, or as Moyſes did with a white ſticke at the red Sea, that as the red ſea deuided it ſelfe and gaue place to <hi>Moyſes</hi> to paſſe through dry, ſo ſhould <hi>Iordan</hi> do to <hi>Theudas.</hi> But <hi>Feſtus</hi> the Roman Preſident, hauing knowledge of <hi>Theudas</hi> practice, armed certein Romanes, ſlue the ſeditious, and brought <hi>Theudas</hi> head
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:9175:30"/>
vpon a long pole from Iordan to Ieruſalem.</p>
               <p>Such ſeditious men and the like euer practiſed po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, to mooue the people to tumults &amp; mutinyes, they are neuer quiet but when they practiſe ſuch policies, then they thinke they haue <hi>Gyges</hi> ring in their hands, that no men ſee them, and they ſuppoſe them ſelues as fortunate, if they effect their purpoſe, as <hi>Polycrates</hi> did of his Ring that hee threw into the ſea and found it againe: yet <hi>Polycrates</hi> fortune was to hang afterward, as <hi>Iudas</hi> and <hi>Theudas</hi> were ſlaine.</p>
               <p>There is another kind of politike practiſers, euen with kings in Court, called <hi>Syrenes aulae,</hi> much made of and eſteemed: but they alſo practiſe in a glaſſe, ſo fickle, that ſlattery endureth no longer then the glaſſe wherein it is practiſed; for when the glaſſe of any wicked practice is broken, the practicer is alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Cicero</hi> gaue a caueat to the Senators, that they ſhould bee carefull whome to beleeue, <hi>Nihil ſubito cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo, ſed ſemper omnia cauendo,</hi> and ſo writes to his frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>Atticus,</hi> Take heede whome you beleeue, <hi>Niſi vultu &amp; fronte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another cryeth out aloud from Greece, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more profitable to many men then diffidence, as ſayth <hi>Euripides,</hi> Few can be excuſed, if accuſation <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> will ſerue: <hi>Auris non fides prabenda,</hi> ſaid <hi>Maecenas</hi> to <hi>Auguſtus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is written of the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> amongſt <note place="margin">Conſtant.</note> many vertues, hee had this fault, that hee permitted pickthanks alwayes to haue acceſſe vnto him. Of ſuch men <hi>Nero</hi> was called <hi>Princeps delatorum,</hi> who allowed the fourth part of the goods of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that were accuſed,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:9175:31"/>
to the accuſers, and therfore were theſe accuſers called in ſcorne, <hi>Quadruplateres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tyberius</hi> the Emperor, when the Senators thought good to abrogate theſe great rewards graunted to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers, <note place="margin">Tiberius his ſaying.</note> ſayd, <hi>Iuraſubuerti, ſi cuſtodes legum amouerentur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So did <hi>Vitellius</hi> puniſh certain Mathematicians with death, by meanes of ſuch ſecret &amp; dangerous accuſers, without licence to anſwere the accuſers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Domitianus</hi> gaue attentiue eare to ſuch as would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe ſecret faults of men, being true or otherwiſe; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as one accuſer accuſed another, being ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that Rome was full of theſe pickthanks, while theſe <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ariſt poli. 5. cap. 15.</note> Emperours reigned; no better then <hi>Dioniſius</hi> the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, who appoynted certaine men, whom he himſelfe named <hi>Sagogidas,</hi> to inform him what euery man ſpake and did.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benhadad</hi> the king of Syria was much vexed in his mind, and ſuſpected ſome of his chiefe ſeruants, &amp; ſayd vnto them, Who betrayeth mee to the king of Iſrael? It was anſwered by one of his chamber, that king <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hadad</hi> could neither ſpeake nor doe any thing in his <note place="margin">4. Reg. 6.</note> priuy chamber, but <hi>Elizeus</hi> the man of God knew it at Dothan.</p>
               <p>It is a true ſaying, that he that is God and Man, doth he are our wicked blaſphemies, and ſeeth our treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous practiſes: which if he ſay, <hi>Quis decipiet Achab vt cadat?</hi> there ſhall want no lying ſpirits to practiſe policy and to deceiue ſuch. <note place="margin">3. Reg. 22</note>
               </p>
               <p>But againe to pick-thanks. <hi>Veſpaſianus,</hi> and after him his ſon, <hi>Titus,</hi> ſo hated ſuch Promoters, that they cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed theſe fellowes to be ſcourged and whipped round about the Theaters in the ſight of the people.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:9175:31"/>
                  <hi>Antonius,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Pius,</hi> decreed that priuy and ſecret accuſers that could not prooue euidently their accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be true, ſhould dye for it, and if their accuſation were prooued, they had what the law permitted them, and ſo diſmiſſed them <hi>cum ignominia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like is ſayd of the Emperour <hi>Opilius Macrinus,</hi> that he could not abide to heare the name of a Pick. <note place="margin">Alex. lib. 4 cap. 22.</note> thanke. Such buſy ſecret accuſers are like <hi>Crates</hi> the Theban, who was ſurnamed, the Dore-opener, for that hee would ruſh into euery mans company to heare what was ſayd, and to ſee what was done: Many ſuch are both in Courts and Countreyes. <hi>Placida loquentes, praua ſtruentes,</hi> ſuch haue ouerthrowne many kings and princes.</p>
               <p>It had bene better for <hi>Alexander</hi> to haue <hi>Epicharmus</hi> ſentence euery where in his mouth, <hi>Memento diffidere,</hi> then to haue <hi>Darius</hi> ſignet vpon his finger in Babylon. And it had bin better for <hi>Caeſar</hi> to haue followed <hi>Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes</hi> counſel before he came to Pharſalia, then to weare <hi>Pompeyes</hi> Ring vpon his finger in Affricke. But ſuch is the force of flattery in Courts and Countreyes, that the flatterer carries the earth vpon his backe, as <hi>Atlas</hi> (as Poets faigne) carries the heauens vpon his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
               <p>The Perſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and the Medes were ſuch flatterers, &amp; that not only to their kings, whom they adore &amp; worſhip as <note place="margin">The flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Perſians.</note> gods, but in ſaluting one another, they would bend &amp; bow them ſelues vnto the ground: <hi>Alexander</hi> the great was contented in Macedonia, to be the ſonne of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther king <hi>Philip,</hi> but in Perſia they made him the ſonne of <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His father <hi>Philip</hi> in like ſort was in Macedonia, but
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:9175:32"/>
when he came &amp; conquered Greece, in any great aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they elected new Magiſtrates, they prayed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Iupiter, Apollo</hi> and <hi>Hercules,</hi> to giue good ſucceſſe to theſe Officers and Magiſtrates: the Argiues ſo flattered <hi>Philip,</hi> that they wrote his name, &amp; named him next after <hi>Hercules,</hi> to be the fourth in their petition and ſupplication to their gods.</p>
               <p>The people ſo flattered <hi>Herod</hi> a wicked king, after he had ſlaine <hi>Iames,</hi> and impriſoned <hi>Peter,</hi> that at his laſt Oration which he made to the Iewes, the people cried out: <hi>Vox dei, non hominis,</hi> but <hi>Herod</hi> preſently fel down <note place="margin">Acts 12.</note> dead and was eaten with wormes.</p>
               <p>So the falſe Prophets flattered the king of Iſrael <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab,</hi> that he ſhould haue victory ouer the Syria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: theſe flattering prophets ſo practiſed with ſuch ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſpirits, that <hi>Achab</hi> was ſlaine by the Syrians, &amp; was brought <note place="margin">3. Reg. 22</note> dead to be buryed in Samatia.</p>
               <p>The Athenia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſo flattered <hi>Demetrius,</hi> that his Image was caryed and borne with <hi>Iupiter, Minerua</hi> &amp; <hi>Mars</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Demetrius much ſlat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in Athens.</note> in the Banner of Peplon, and <hi>Demetrius</hi> was the fourth, but he died in priſon.</p>
               <p>The Athenians lodged and entertained ſtrangers to ſee, to heare, and to learne ſome newes; any lying flatterer might be welcome to Athens.</p>
               <p>But others loue not to be ſo flattered, as <hi>Octauius Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> and <hi>Alexander Seuerus,</hi> who ſo hated Flatterers, that they had ſpies abroad, to finde them out: and if <note place="margin">Elattery hated of Auguſtus.</note> any ſeemed eyther with words or outward behauiour to be like Flatterers, they ſhould bee ſtreight baniſhed the Courts of theſe two Emperours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caſſander,</hi> ſaluted of all men as a king, and ſo called, hee loued not to be flattered, nor to vſurpe the name
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:9175:32"/>
of a king, and though he was written vnto by the name of a king, yet he refuſed to be ſo called. Neyther would <note place="margin">Porus. Diodor. lib. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Porus</hi> K. of India, after he was conquered by <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, ſuffer any man to cal him king. This ſeemed to be great modeſty, to refuſe the names of kings being offred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yet many Tyrants vſurp the names of kings, and many make meanes to become kings, Emperours, and Princes, practiſing many policyes by trecherie, by murther, by poyſoning and killing: &amp; many prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe meanes to become Officers and Magiſtrates, and yet would not be ſeene practiſers therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>Sectio 10.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N Rome ſuch polycies were practiſed, ſuch ſutes were made to become ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">The elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Magiſtrats in Rome. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Thucid. lib. 3.</note> Conſull, Pretor, Tribune, Cenſor or Aedile, that the 35. Tribes were ſo flattered and followed in <hi>Martius</hi> field with money, with friends, and with all meanes poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to become Magiſtrates and officers within the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Rome, and at that time the Arte of Flattery was there to bee taught and learned.</p>
               <p>There, they that were to be elected, ſtood before the Senators and Conſuls, clothed all in white garments, without gownes, for that was a garment ſuſpicious, and not at any time to be ſuffred by the law, leſt they might eary ſome rewards to corrupt the people vnder them; and after they were thus choſen, they were accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed from <hi>Martius</hi> field, when they had flattered the <note place="margin">Alex. lib. 4. cap. 3.</note> people with thankes for their election: then they went vnto the Capitoll, and from the Capitoll they were brought vnto their houſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:9175:33"/>
This kinde of election continued but a ſhort time, yet flattery endured longer, and was practiſed at any change of Magiſtrates or Officers, yet <hi>Lu. Craſſus</hi> could not be brought before <hi>Q. Scauola</hi> to giue thankes vnto the people, leſt hee ſhould ſeeme to haue the name of a flatterer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paulus Aemilius,</hi> when he was choſen Conſul to goe with an army into Perſia, and was for to come vnto <note place="margin">Paul. Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milius ſaying.</note> the Capitoll to thank the people, according to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane cuſtome, he refuſed, &amp; ſayd, If they could find a fitter man to go againſt king <hi>Perſeus,</hi> he was wel conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to yeeld againe his new Conſulſhip vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to make their election of another: he thought it not fit to flatter the people with faire wordes.</p>
               <p>Such was <hi>Phocion</hi> in Athens, hee would make no meanes vnto the people, neither would <hi>Phocion</hi> be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at any time of election of newe Officers or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates: he would neyther ſend nor ſpeake for any Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice <note place="margin">Phocion.</note> in Athens: the Athenians vſed ſo often to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt people for Offices and Honors to become Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, that <hi>Demosthenes</hi> cryed out, that <hi>Populus et pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> were the Monſters of Athens, as <hi>Capitolium</hi> and <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> were in Rome.</p>
               <p>Such was <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> a man moſt iuſt and moſt quiet among the Athenians: but theſe were rare men to bee found. But <hi>Cliſophus</hi> could halt in Macedonia with king <hi>Philip,</hi> &amp; ſaid, he had alſo the Gowt aſwel as King <hi>Philip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cleo</hi> could better pleaſe <hi>Alexander</hi> with his flattery, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Caliſthenes</hi> could do with his philoſophy. That Prince <note place="margin">Cleo, a great flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer.</note> ought not to be called a Prince, where trueth dare not be ſpoken, &amp; in whoſe Court men are often conſumed more by flatterers in the time of peace, then by the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:9175:33"/>
enemies in the warres: ſo <hi>Q. Curtius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Regum opes ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius aſſentatio, quàm hoſtis euertit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a people in ſome parte of Ethiopia, called <note place="margin">Diodor. li. 4. cap. 1.</note> Cathaei, that if their king do halt or be lame in any part of his body, his houſhold ſeruants muſt likewiſe halt and be lame in the ſelfeſame place where the King is lame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alcamenes</hi> was much praiſed in Athens, for that he made the halting Image of <hi>Vulcan</hi> to ſtand vpright in ſuch garments that hid the deformity of his halting; And yet for all the skill of <hi>Alcamenes,</hi> ſayd <hi>Cicero, Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cic. de diuinat. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>habebant deum,</hi> the Athenians had but a lame god. I feare, that many beſide the Athenians, with <hi>Vulcans</hi> garments, would fayne hide their halting, and would ſeeme to goe vpright, though they halt with <hi>Vulcan</hi> for all <hi>Alcamenes</hi> skill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pilate</hi> had a better garment that hid his faults before <hi>Tib. Caeſar;</hi> for, being accuſed that he put an innocent man to death, which was Chriſt, hee put on Chriſtes vnſeamed coate before he came to <hi>Caeſar:</hi> to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when <note place="margin">Math. Weſtmin.</note> 
                  <hi>Pilate</hi> came, <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſo imbraced him, that men muſed much thereat; but after <hi>Pilate</hi> departed out of <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſight, <hi>Caeſar</hi> being as before incenſed againſt him, ſent in haſte for him againe, and he hauing Chriſts coat on, was in like ſort embraced and entertayned of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour as before: for he could finde no fault in <hi>Pilate</hi> while Chriſtes coat was on him: a farre better garment then <hi>Vulcans</hi> garment: yet more ſeek <hi>Vulcans</hi> Garment to hide their halting, then do ſeeke Chriſtes coate to learne to go vpright: but theſe Practiſers, if they may not be helped with <hi>Vulcans</hi> garment, they will vſe <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantes</hi> policy.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:9175:34"/>
At the ſacrificing of <hi>Iphigenia, Timantes</hi> practiſed his beſt ſkill to paint the lamentation of <hi>Menelaus,</hi> the ſadnes of <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> the ſobbes and ſighes of <hi>Aiax,</hi> but ſuch was the extreme paſſion and penſiueneſſe of <hi>Agamem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Plin. 35. cap. 10.</note> for his daughter, that <hi>Timantes</hi> could not ſet it downe in colours, but was forced to throw a Veile o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Agamemnons</hi> head, to excuſe the defect of his ſkill in ſo tragicall a ſight. Many do practiſe the like policy, <note place="margin">Vel. lib. 8. cap. 11.</note> that if they can not effect their ſkill to their purpoſe, then they practiſe how they may hide their defect, and couer it as <hi>Timantes</hi> did couer <hi>Agamemnons</hi> head.</p>
               <p>There be many ſicke of the ſickenes called Tarantu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la which if men would looke vpon them, they ſeemed <note place="margin">Alex. lib 2. cap. 17</note> as men halfe dead. No remedy was found for this Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tula in Apulia, but ſuch as was in Greece vſed againſt phrenſie and lunacie, which was the playing of Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrels. Many are ſicke of this ſicknes Tarantula.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>Sectio. 11.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ALOMON,</hi> a man indued with ſingular wiſdome, taught how me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be cured that were poſſeſſed with Deuils, and taught alſo how Deuils might bee driuen away, which the Iewes for a long time vſed after <hi>Salomon:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Deuils ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſian. Ioſeph. li. 8 cap. 2.</note> This is that which <hi>Ioſephus</hi> ſaw being in place himſelfe, one <hi>Eleazarus</hi> healing diuers that were violently tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and vexed with euill ſpirits in preſence of <hi>Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſian</hi> the Emperour and his ſonne <hi>Titus,</hi> Tribunes, and diuers Captaines, by laying vnto the noſtrilles of the man poſſeſſed a Ring, hauing in the ſignet of the Ring a roote which <hi>Salomon</hi> ſhewed, that by the ſmell
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:9175:34"/>
of that roote, the euill ſpirit ſhould come out through the ſicke mans noſe, whom the Iew <hi>Eleazarus</hi> adiured neuer to returne to that man againe, making mention of <hi>Salomons</hi> name vnto the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>And for that the Emperor <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> being then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with his ſouldiers, might know that theſe men tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in this ſort were healed, <hi>Eleazarus</hi> ſet a Baſon full of water in their ſight, and charged the euill ſpirit at his departing out from the man, to ſhewe a certeine ſigne in the water to the beholders, that by the ſight thereof, they might beleeue the Arte of <hi>Eleazarus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like is written in <hi>Tobias,</hi> of the ſpirit <hi>Aſmodeus,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tob. 8.</note> which was commaunded to come out of <hi>Sara Raguels</hi> daughter, by the Lyuer of a Fiſh.</p>
               <p>So diuers are vexed with deuils, that ſome carry do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils in their pokes in glaſſes, ſome in Images in their chambers, and ſome haue them in their Temples wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped and adored, and vſe to aske counſell of them: for they are poſſeſt with deuils, that aske counſell of deuils.</p>
               <p>To ſuch went <hi>Achab,</hi> when he went for counſell to <hi>Baals</hi> Prophets, to know the euents of his warres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <note place="margin">3. Reg. 22</note> him and <hi>Meſa</hi> king of Moab.</p>
               <p>To ſuch went <hi>Saul,</hi> when he went to <hi>Phaetoniſſa</hi> the witch at Endor, to aske counſel for the like purpoſe, as <note place="margin">1. Sam. 18</note> 
                  <hi>Ahab</hi> did, to know how hee ſhould ſpeed againſt the Philiſtines.</p>
               <p>And to ſuch went <hi>Ahazia,</hi> when he went to <hi>Beelze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bub</hi> the god of Accaron, to know if he might recouer <note place="margin">4. Reg. 1.</note> his health.</p>
               <p>Many goe to <hi>Beelzebub</hi> the god of Accaron, and to <hi>Baals,</hi> Prophets and the like, to learne how they may practiſe policy, as <hi>Hazael</hi> did when he went to <hi>Elizeus,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:9175:35"/>
pretending to knowe if king <hi>Benhadad</hi> his Maſter ſhould recouer his health: but <hi>Hazael</hi> practiſed ſuch polycies, beſides the ſtrangling of the king his Maſter, that it made <hi>Elizeus</hi> to weep, knowing the tyranny that <hi>Hazael</hi> would practiſe againſt Iſrael.</p>
               <p>Many ſuch ſeditious perſons practiſe the like miſchief in their hearts, as <hi>Hazael</hi> did, which if men might ſee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, as <hi>Elizeus</hi> did, or might open their hearts &amp; make an Anatomy of their bodies, as the Athenians did by <hi>Ariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thomenes</hi> the Meſſenian, which being taken captiue by the Athenians, they bowelled him, and found his heart full of hayres, <hi>Cer piloſum</hi> (as <hi>Plinie</hi> ſayth) no doubt, many would bee found to haue <hi>cordapiloſa,</hi> as <hi>Ariſtho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Plin. 11. cap. 37.</note> was among the Athenians.</p>
               <p>Some Emperours of Rome had the Image of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune made of glaſſe, &amp; placed it in their gallery, which <note place="margin">The image of fortune made of glaſſe.</note> ſtood alwayes there from one Emperour to another, to ſignifie the vncertaynety of mans life, and to put them in remembrance how frayle and fickle mans ſtate is.</p>
               <p>And therefore one of the Emperors hauing a glaſſe in his hand, after hee dranke, threw the glaſſe againſt the walles, and ſaid, This reſembleth the ſtate of an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour in Rome. Such was the continuance of the Emperors of Rome, that ſome were ſlaine in the fields, ſome in the towne, ſome in their chambers, and ſome in their beds: Such was their practice to come to the Empire, and ſuch was the policy vſed in like maner, to deſtroy and to murther them in their Empires.</p>
               <p>Of theſe and ſuch like men <hi>Diogenes</hi> the Cinick ſaid, that they were thrice moſt miſerable men, to aske cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> of deuils, and go to the glaſſe of <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres</hi> the Sorcerers of Egypt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:9175:35"/>
Others there bee, that practiſe their policy in the glaſſe of vſury, much freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted amongſt Citizens; for it is a <hi>maxime</hi> with them, <hi>Nihil turpe cum lucro,</hi> any kind of gayne is good with the vſurer, they loue it as they <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> loue themſelues, <hi>Sanguis, vita &amp; eorum anima pecunia,</hi> It is as deare vnto them as the bloud of their bodies, or the life of their ſoules, whoſe heauen is the world, like <hi>Vliſses,</hi> who preferred his country of Ithaca before e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, whoſe bellie is their god with the Epicure, and whoſe harts are ſo hardned, that neither the late plague, nor the Peſtilence, nor any puniſhment which God doth inflict vpon them, can mollify their ſtony hearts.</p>
               <p>Vſurers were baniſhed from Athens by the Law of <hi>Solon,</hi> and their Tables of Vſurie burned in Athens, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> which was the pureſt fire that euer <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> ſaw, as he him ſelfe ſaid.</p>
               <p>And in Sparta, by the Lawe of <hi>Licurgus,</hi> no V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer might dwell within the Confines of Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia. Such Vſurers and Monopolies were alſo baniſhed from all Aſia, by <hi>Lucullus:</hi> and for that the name of an Vſurer ſhould not be named within Aſia, hee vſed the lawe of <hi>Amneſtia</hi> by <hi>Thraſibulus</hi> made in Athens. <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>So did <hi>Cate</hi> then Conſull, cleare all Sicilia from V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers and Monopolies: theſe be <hi>Sorices Reip.</hi> the Rats of a Common wealth: theſe be the Moths that eate mens clothes on their backs: theſe be the Wormes that breed in the Bee-hiues, that deuoure all the hony.</p>
               <p>There be others that be ambitious practiſers, more dangerous, which hunt for to become Magiſtrates and Officers: againſt theſe, the law of <hi>Ostraciſmos</hi> was put <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> in execution in Athens, and the law <hi>Petaliſmes</hi> in Syra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſa, and euery where ſuch were baniſhed <hi>Igne &amp; aqua;</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:9175:36"/>
theſe be clymers and practiſers how to be mighty, and to be aduaunced vnto greatnes: theſe were of the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Athens, <hi>Noctua, populus, &amp; Draco,</hi> of whom <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes</hi> ſpeaketh.</p>
               <p>In the time of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, none would he ſuffer great beſides himſelfe in all the earth. In the time of <hi>Antiochus,</hi> none great in all Aſia but hee. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Romanes, none but one <hi>Pompey</hi> the great. <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> But in theſe dayes many practiſe their policy to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come great, againſt the rule of the Philoſopher, who ſaith, <hi>Neminem vnum magnum facere, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lawyers alſo haue their glaſſe, where they may ſee <hi>Balaam</hi> ryding on his Aſſe: <hi>Balac</hi> attended on <note place="margin">The Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs of Iudges, and of Iuſtice.</note> with Moabites &amp; Madianites, with bribes and rewards in their hands to haue <hi>Balaams</hi> counſell, which might put them in remembrance of corrupt Iudges, and greedy Lawyers. In this glaſſe, they ſhall ſee alſo <hi>Moloc</hi> with a reaching hand: But there is a better ſight in this Glaſſe, the Images of Iudges without hands: the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Kings, without eyes: and Iuſtice it ſelfe pictured without a head, to ſignify, that Kings ſhould be without affection, and Iudges without corruption: <hi>Ne gratia,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>precio, odio vel timore eludi poſſit Iuſtitia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The vſe of Glaſſes were made to this purpoſe, to reforme and to inſtruct men of outward and inward faults.</p>
               <p>Such a Glaſſe had <hi>Plato,</hi> to reforme Drunkards, and furious haſty men, that by beholding of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues <note place="margin">Platoes glaſſe.</note> in <hi>Platoes</hi> Glaſſe, they might ſee how they were depryued of all their ſences, and left without any humane part that ſhould be in reaſonable men, and that by looking in this Glaſſe, they might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:9175:36"/>
themſelues: <hi>Ad hoc vtile eſt nobis Speculum:</hi> A Glaſſe is neceſſary herein.</p>
               <p>Such a Glaſſe had <hi>Socrates</hi> to ſhew his Schollers, that they which were moſt beautifull and goodly, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. Plu, in Timokon.</note> wanting no comely forme of body, might learne by <hi>Socrates</hi> Glaſſe, not to deface that Beauty, or deforme that body with any foule vice, or filthy fault of the minde: And if they were lame, crooked, or any way deformed, in the ſame Glaſſe, <hi>Socrates</hi> taught them how to amend and to counteruaile the deformity of the body, with wiſdome, knowledge, and vertue of the mind: <hi>Ingenii cultu morum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> probi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate penſarent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was the vſe of the Glaſſe, ſayd <hi>Seneca,</hi> to amend faults, and not to learne faults; not to learne Idolatry, as <hi>Neſtorius</hi> did, to make Mirrors of men; or like <hi>Narciſſus,</hi> to flatter our ſelues. <note place="margin">Narciſſus glaſse.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Archimedes</hi> Glaſſe was much more commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Syracuſa to deceiue the Romanes his enemyes by his Glaſſe, then we by our owne Glaſſes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue <note place="margin">Archime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des glaſſe.</note> our ſelues.</p>
               <p>It was lawfull for <hi>Archimedes</hi> to practiſe policy, to burne Townes, Cyties and Shippes by his Glaſſe, to deſtroy the enemyes of Syracuſa.</p>
               <p>Next this Glaſſe of flattery, commeth in the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Glaſse of Idolatry.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Neſtorius</hi> and <hi>Narciſſus</hi> deceiued themſelues &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, what wonder is it that <hi>Zeuxes</hi> painted a Bitch on a Table ſo liuely, that Dogges at the ſight thereof barked? Or that <hi>Parrhaſius</hi> painted a Mare in ſuch ſort, that Horſes neighed at the lookng on it?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:9175:37"/>
Neither of that picture which <hi>Praxiteles</hi> made, which was the Image of a beautifull comely woman of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to ſtand in a Temple at Gnydos, that ſome youth <note place="margin">Aelian. 2. de var. hiſt Plin. li. 36 cap. 5.</note> of that citie ſuppoſed the Image to bee no leſſe a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, then the Dogges that barked at <hi>Xeuxes</hi> Bitch, or the Horſes that neighed at <hi>Parrhaſius</hi> Mare, or the Bull that lowed at the braſen cow in Syracuſa: but I thinke not ſo of the woodden Cow of Creet, the mother of Monſters.</p>
               <p>But theſe are things naturall and eaſie to be beleeued in Beaſts, becauſe they are beaſts: but for people of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and vnderſtanding, to loue Images and pictures, &amp; to honour &amp; worſhip them, is more beaſtly then beaſts them ſelues, becauſe they ſhould not be beaſts.</p>
               <p>Rome, of all kingdoms and countries, was beholden to Images: for when <hi>Camillus</hi> had ouercome the Vei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, <note place="margin">Plut. in Camil.</note> one of <hi>Camillus</hi> Soldiers asked <hi>Iunoes</hi> image, <hi>Vis migrare Romam?</hi> Who anſwered, <hi>Libenter velo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the Image of Fortune in <hi>Coriolianus</hi> time, at the dedication of her Temple, gaue great thankes vnto <note place="margin">Plut. in Camil.</note> the Matrones of Rome, and ſayd, <hi>Recte me dedicaſtis Matronae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The citie of Rome being vexed with a long plague, was admoniſhed by <hi>Sybillaes</hi> books, to ſend to <hi>Epidau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> for <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> image, who followed the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours <note place="margin">Oro. lib. 3. cap. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>in forma Serpentis,</hi> from <hi>Epidaurus</hi> to Rome, and healed the Romane plague, ſo that Rome was ſo full of Images, that <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayd, <hi>Quot linguae hominum Romae, tot nomina Deorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Athens were but fewe leſſe in number then in Rome, they had as many Images in Athens, as they had Poets to faine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or Painters to paint them, they
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:9175:37"/>
had ſo many Images, that they had an Altar <hi>ignoto deo,</hi> that ſome Philoſophers thought good to baniſh all Poets and Painters out of Athens.</p>
               <p>In Egypt, the mother of Idolatry, were the Images of all kinde of Beaſts, of Serpents, of Fowles &amp; of fiſhes worſhipped as gods, <hi>O ſeculum Daemoniorum, non De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore <hi>Iehu</hi> vſing this ſtratagem to deſtroy theſe Idols, fayned a day of great ſolemnity and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice <note place="margin">The ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem of Iehu. 4. Reg. 10</note> to <hi>Baal,</hi> and called al the prophets, prieſts &amp; frends of king <hi>Achab</hi> to this ſolemnity, ſaying, that he would, as <hi>Achab</hi> had done before, ſacrifice to <hi>Baal:</hi> and hauing them all within the Temple, commaunded certayne ſoldiers to inuade and kill them.</p>
               <p>So God taught <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuch ſtratagems in Egipt againſt <hi>Pharao,</hi> and to <hi>Ioſua</hi> at Iericho, and at Ai, to deſtroy the enemies of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergamenes,</hi> king of Ethiope, vſing the like policy as <hi>Iehu</hi> did, to make an end of all the prieſts of Ethiope, who by their Lawe had authority to elect a King, ſo <note place="margin">Dioder. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 4. cap. 1.</note> long to raigne as pleaſed thoſe prieſts to ſuffer him, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled the like policy as <hi>Iehu</hi> did, to ſolemnize a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to their gods, where he ſlue them euery one.</p>
               <p>So is diſſimulation lawfull in ſuch and like actions. So <hi>Chuſa</hi> diſſembled with <hi>Abſolom,</hi> and ſaid, God ſaue <note place="margin">2. Sam. 17</note> King <hi>Abſolom,</hi> as though he had refuſed and forſaken king <hi>Dauid,</hi> and was become an obedient ſeruant to <hi>Abſolom.</hi> By this meanes he ouerthrew <hi>Achitophel</hi> and his counſell, and afterward <hi>Abſolom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Samuel</hi> diſſembled his comming to Bethlehem to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynt <hi>Dauid</hi> king ouer Iſrael, pretending that he came <note place="margin">1. Sam. 16</note> to do ſacrifice, as the Lord commaunded.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:9175:38"/>
So <hi>Dauid</hi> fayned himſelfe madde, leſt he ſhould go <note place="margin">1. Sam. 21</note> with king <hi>Achiſh</hi> to fight againſt Iſrael.</p>
               <p>Diſſimulation therefore may be vſed, yea euen in <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Plat. de Rep. 5.</note> Courts, as <hi>Plato</hi> ſayd, that Princes may diſſemble, to preuent greater harmes to their ſubiects, and may vſe ſuch policies as the Phiſician doeth to his patients, to put poyſon in his drugges, to heale his patients.</p>
               <p>Yet I remember <hi>Auguſtines</hi> ſaying of diſſimulation, that there be many kinds of diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; in ſome of theſe ſaith <hi>Auguſtin, Non magna culpa, non tamen ſine culpa.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Aug. in 5. Pſal.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe <hi>Licurgus</hi> held it neceſſary, that both diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation and ambition ſhould be ſometimes vſed to offend in the leaſt Iuſtice, to performe a greater Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp;c. Plu. in Pol.</note> and yet not allowing that, but <hi>palliata Iuſtitia,</hi> and that for neceſſities ſake.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Cato</hi> diſsembled and ſuffred ſedition in his houſe among his ſeruants.</p>
               <p>Where the Lyons skin, ſaith <hi>Lyſander,</hi> reacheth not, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Plu. in Cat.</note> it muſt be ſowed to the Fox skyn: So that Princes muſt be of the nature of the Lyon, and yet be as wiſe and as wary as the Fox.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Hanibal,</hi> by a flattering ſtratagem ſaid, that thoſe that would go to the enemyes to learne and to know <note place="margin">Front. lib. 3. cap. 3.</note> the counſell and ſeruice of the enemyes, were not to be called Traytors, but the onely expert Soldiers, &amp; moſt worthy to be eſteemed. Then were they more bold, and went the next night as they had appointed. The Romanes hauing often times vnderſtanding of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty of <hi>Hanibal,</hi> tooke them and cut off their hands, and ſent them to <hi>Hannibal</hi> without hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diodorus</hi> hauing a garryſon in Amphipolis, ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <note place="margin">Diodorus garriſon at Amphip.</note> two thouſand Thracians which were ſeditious in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:9175:38"/>
the towne, fearing ſome conſpiracy againſt Amphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis, fayned that certayne ſhips of the enemy ſayled at the next ſhore, which ſhould be a great ſpoyle to the Thracians, and moſt eaſie to obtayne. The Thracians being greedy and ſeditious Souldiers, gathered their company together, and ſet out of Amphipolis with great hope of a good pray, who as ſoone as they were out of the City, the Captain commaunded the Gates to be ſhut and kept them out, &amp; ſo they cleered Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phypolis: Such policyes muſt be vſed againſt falſe ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious people, to finde them out, to ryd and cleere them from honeſt people.</p>
               <p>By ſuch diſſimulation through ſedition, <hi>Hanibal</hi> got Tarentum. So <hi>Marcellus,</hi> by corrupting of <hi>Soſiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> wanne Syracuſa. So <hi>Philip</hi> of Macedon, by the <note place="margin">Cic. do diuinat. 2</note> like, got Samos of <hi>Apollonius.</hi> He could ſo Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pizin with <hi>Pythia,</hi> as <hi>Demoſtenes</hi> ſayth, that none might haue acceſſe to <hi>Apollo,</hi> but <hi>Philip</hi> of Macedon.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Philip</hi> being admoniſhed by the ſelfe ſame <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia,</hi> to take heed and to looke to <hi>Quadriga,</hi> though hee <note place="margin">Cic. de Fate.</note> cauſed ſtreight all the Coaches, waggons, and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ottes within Macedonia, to be taken aſunder, and with all care ſhunned &amp; auoyded the place in Booetia, called <hi>Quadriga,</hi> yet <hi>Philip</hi> could not auoyd that <hi>Quadriga,</hi> which was written vpon the hylt of <hi>Pauſanias</hi> ſword, with the which <hi>Philip</hi> was ſlayne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> practiſed no ſuch policy, for he quieted a Legion of ſeditious Souldiers with one word, <hi>Num vos pudeat, Quirites?</hi> Are ye not aſhamed, you Romans, of your ſeditious practice? They ſuſpecting that <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> had intelligence of their practice, they were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently reconciled and pacified with that word, &amp; with the ſight of <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:9175:39"/>
With the like word, <hi>Demades</hi> an Orator of Athens, being taken captiue by <hi>Philip</hi> of Macedon, with many more poore captiue Greekes, ouer which <hi>Philip</hi> ſo try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed, dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing &amp; feaſting with Garlands &amp; Crowns and taunting them with ſpitefull words, <hi>Demades</hi> ſpake boldly vnto him: <hi>Nonne te pudeat Philippe, cùm fortuna tuate Agamemnonem fecit, tein tuis opprobriis eſſe Thar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitem?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The ſaying of Demae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> Art not thou aſhamed, king <hi>Philip,</hi> whom For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune made equall with <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> thou to make thy ſelfe in ſcoffing equall to <hi>Tharſites?</hi> Vpon which words, <hi>Philip</hi> diſmiſſed the poore Captiues, and entred in league with the Athenians.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Alex, Seuerus</hi> clean contrary to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> perceiuing as <hi>Caeſar</hi> did, many ſeditious ſouldiers conſpyring to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, diſmiſſed them out of the Army, cleered his Campe, and ſaid, <hi>Diſcedite Quirites, deponite arma:</hi> for he was as glad to be ryd of ſuch Souldiers, as they were glad to be ryd of ſo ſeuere a Captaine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cornelius Gracchus,</hi> a very eloquent Romane, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſo factious &amp; ſo ſeditious, that he was euer wont to haue ſecretly behind him, one of his ſeruants, a Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician with an Iuory Flute, to mooue, to ſtirre, and to <note place="margin">Cic. de Orat. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp;c. Plat. de leg.</note> giue life to his Maſters ſpeach to mooue ſedition. This <hi>Gracchus</hi> little eſteemed <hi>Platoes</hi> lawes, who iudged eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way a ſeditious man worthy of death, as the law was: <hi>Si quis priuatim pacem bellumue fecerit, capitale eſto:</hi> yet had <hi>Gracchus</hi> rather be ſlain among ſeditious men, him ſelfe being chiefe ſeditious, then to liue in peace, and to mayntaine peace in his country at Rome.</p>
               <p>How much better was <hi>Egeſias</hi> a Phyloſopher in Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raena, who not onely perſwaded againſt factious and ſeditious men, but alſo inueyed againſtal wickednes of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:9175:39"/>
life, exhorting to abhorre vice and to loue vertue.</p>
               <p>Such counſell gaue <hi>Egeſias</hi> to the Cyraenians, as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> gaue to the Athenians, whoſe precept was alwaies <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Laere. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Sole.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſule quae optima, non quae ſuauiſſima.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By which perſwaſion, he ſo mortified the Cyraenians that they thought it better to dye, then to lyue. But that good practiſe of this Phyloſopher, was by <hi>Ptholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mei</hi> king of Egypt put to ſilence, leſt too many became honeſt and vertuous.</p>
               <p>Such a Phyloſopher to perſwade, and ſuch a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher to teach mortification, were wel worthy of a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <note place="margin">Laert. in Ariſtip.</note> Image, were it not that ſom kind of people would eſteeme more of the Image then of the man, as <hi>Dioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> made more of <hi>Iupiters</hi> golden Garment, then of <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Iupiter,</hi> more of <hi>Aeſculepius</hi> golden beard, then of <hi>Aeſculapius:</hi> It was euer his ſpeach for money.</p>
               <p>Seditious men euer eſteemed the golde of the Temple, more then the Temple; the gold of the Altar, more then the Altar: they be like the Moabites, alwaies <note place="margin">4. Reg. 3.</note> ready for the ſpoyle.</p>
               <p>Theſe bee they which <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt calles <hi>Prognies</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 3</note> 
                  <hi>Viperarum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may be ſayd of theſe wicked Practiſers, that they know not of what ſpirit they are, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſayd to <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> when they would haue fire from heauen to burne Samaria. <hi>Neſcitis cuius Spiritus eſtis.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Many practiſe ſuch policyes with ſuch furyes as the Syrians that went from Damaſco with two eyes to kyll <hi>Elizeus</hi> at Dothan, but they were brought blinde <note place="margin">4. Reg. 6.</note> from Dothan to Samaria among their enemies.</p>
               <p>Others practiſe the like policy with <hi>Gehezi,</hi> and run after <hi>Naaman</hi> the Syrian for gifts &amp; rewards, vntill the <note place="margin">4. Reg. 5.</note>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:9175:40"/>
leproſy of <hi>Naaman</hi> come vpon them and their houſes for euer.</p>
               <p>Some truſting to their ſtrength, put their hands to many dangers, like <hi>Milo Cretoniates,</hi> who drew a great yron wedge out of a ſtrong cloue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oake with one hand, <note place="margin">Gel. li. 15. cap. 16.</note> &amp; thruſt the other hand into the cleft where the wedge was, but the oake faſtned vpon his hand, and held him vntill wild beaſts came to deuoure him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hermes</hi> the Egyptian ſayd, that vngodlines is a very <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hermes. cap. 12.</note> heauy ſicknes to the ſoule of man, who is neuer quiet, nor reſteth, but in actions of vngodlines.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antiochus</hi> was ſo vngodly a king, that he was wont to ſay, that he would make Ieruſalem a graue to bury the Iewes. <note place="margin">2. Mac. 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benhadad</hi> would bragge, that the duſt of Samaria would not ſuffice, that euery one of his ſoldiers ſhould <note place="margin">3. Reg. 20</note> haue a handfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sennacherib</hi> was wont to bragge of king <hi>Ezechias,</hi> that neyther God nor man might deliuer him out of <note place="margin">4. Reg. 19</note> his hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dripetine, Mithidrates</hi> daughter, Queene of Laodicea, had double teeth ſet in a rowe, one row beſide another, in ſuch deformed ſort, that it loathed any man to looke vpon her: and yet not ſo lothſome to behold, as to heare the brags and blaſphemies of theſe blaſphemers.</p>
               <p>The Greekes yeelded diuine honours to them that would kill a Tyrant, neyther can it bee a greater ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice <note place="margin">Alawe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants in Greece.</note> to the gods, ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> then the death of a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, <hi>Spolia opima Ioui,</hi> A rich ſpoyle vnto <hi>Iupiter.</hi> Wherefore <hi>Hermodius</hi> and <hi>Ariſtogiton,</hi> two Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:9175:40"/>
of Athens, for killing of <hi>Piſiſtratus</hi> the Tyrant, had graunted them for honour, that no man ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be called after their names in Athens, for that they were much plagued by Tyrants.</p>
               <p>In Greece, a Lawe was made, that <hi>Tyrannorum filii conſcii parentum ſceleris, haud ſecus morte et exilio mulcten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> that Tyrants Children ſhould be banyſhed or dye with their parents.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>Sectio. 12.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>ARIVS Signet vpon <hi>Alexanders</hi> hand mooued much the Macedonians to doubt <note place="margin">Darius Signet.</note> of their kings fauour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pompeyes</hi> Signet vpon <hi>Caeſars</hi> finger, much ſpited the Romanes that were <hi>Pompeyes</hi> friends.</p>
               <p>The Signet of <hi>Marcellus</hi> the Conſull vpon <hi>Hanibals</hi> finger, being ſlain in an ambuſh, ſo aſtoniſhed the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, <note place="margin">Marcellus Signet.</note> that <hi>Criſpinus</hi> in great haſte ſent Letters to Salapia and to other ports and townes about Apulia, that they ſhould not giue credit vnto <hi>Hanibals</hi> Letters, though they were ſealed with <hi>Marcellus</hi> Signet.</p>
               <p>It was the maner of <hi>Alexander,</hi> after hee had conquered <hi>Darius,</hi> when hee wrote his Leters to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, to ſeale them with the Signet of <hi>Darius,</hi> and when he wrote to Macedonia, he vſed his owne Signet.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> (after king <hi>Mithridates</hi> was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued by <hi>Pompey,)</hi> ſoone vanquiſhed king <hi>Pharnaces, Mithridates</hi> ſonne, without any great warres, but by yeelding of his Crown and his Signet vnto <hi>Caeſar:</hi> ſo he
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:9175:41"/>
wrote to his friend <hi>Anitus</hi> to Rome, but theſe three words, <hi>Veni, vidi, vici:</hi> No Nation reſiſted <hi>Caeſar</hi> after he had conquered the Gaules, but his owne nation the Romanes.</p>
               <p>Diuiſions ouerthrew kingdomes and Empyres, ſo was Greece by Graecians, and not by <hi>Philip</hi> of Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: ſo were the Iſraelites after their diuiſion into two kingdomes, ouerthrowen within them ſelues by their owne nation the Iſraelites.</p>
               <p>The Romanes, though not equall in number to the Spaniards, nor in ſtrength to the French men, nor in ſubtilty to the Affricans, nor in knowledge to the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, yet in time the Romanes maſtered all theſe, and many more nations, <hi>Armis et viribus,</hi> ſayth <hi>Vigetius, Pietate et religione,</hi> ſayth <hi>Cicero:</hi> but moſt writers af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, <note place="margin">Viget. lib. 1. cap. 28</note> that the Romanes became Conquerours <hi>Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate et vnitate:</hi> which is the onely cauſe of all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cotys</hi> of Thracia ſeemed herein to imitate the Romanes, who was certified that the Athenians had graunted him to bee free Denizin of Athens: and I will (ſayd <hi>Cotys)</hi> make all the Athenians free in Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, <note place="margin">Val. Max. li. 3. cap. 7</note> and wil make Athens and Thracia all one, <hi>Sic Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciam Athenis aequauit Cotys.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſower of all diſcord is Sathan the Serpent, that ſoweth Tares amongſt good Wheat, while we ſleepe, <note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> We haue no helpe againſt this Serpent, but watching and praying.</p>
               <p>The Hebrues that were bitten by Serpents in the wildernes, were healed by looking vpon the brazen <note place="margin">Numb. 21</note> Serpent in that wildernes.</p>
               <p>The Egyptians could ſaue themſelues from Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:9175:41"/>
of Ethiopia, by their Birds Ibides.</p>
               <p>The Arabians had remedies againſt their venemous red Serpents, by eating of an Arabia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fruit, where thoſe <note place="margin">Diodor.</note> Serpents bred.</p>
               <p>The Graecians by the counſell of <hi>Theophraſtus,</hi> and practice of <hi>Iſmenias,</hi> had their remedies againſt the ſtinging of Vipers.</p>
               <p>The Apulians had their ſalue to ſaue them from the <note place="margin">Alex. li. 2. cap. 17</note> biting of Tarantula, by muſike.</p>
               <p>The Romans found meanes to mitigate the plague in Rome, as you haue heard <hi>clauo fixo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But a greater plague ceaſed in Iſrael by <hi>Iaels</hi> knocking <note place="margin">Iud. 4.</note> a great naile into <hi>Siſeraes</hi> temples.</p>
               <p>Yet againſt the Serpents teeth which <hi>Medea</hi> ſowed, whence ſprang armed men out of the earth, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured one another, no helpe, no remedy, was found againſt theſe Serpents.</p>
               <p>The viperous biting of ſeditious treacherous men that bite a great way off, that no man ſhall ſee them, nor know them before they haue bitten, <hi>Non prius intelligas proditorem, quàm proditus ſis,</hi> ſayth <hi>Seneca.</hi> How then ſhal we preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuch with all the wiſdom we haue, or puniſh <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſuch with all the Lawes wee haue? For ſayth <hi>Cicero, Crimen conceptum aut cogitatum, paenam non meretur.</hi> Faultes conceyued and thought on, which no man knoweth but God himſelfe, ought not to be puniſhed: for (ſayth <hi>Cato) Voluntates non ſunt legibus obnoxiae:</hi> A mans thought is vnder no law, but vnder Gods lawe.</p>
               <p>But yet in another place <hi>Cicero</hi> vrged before the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators, that <hi>Clodius</hi> ſeruant, for that he thought to kyll <hi>Pompey</hi> the great, being then a ſole Conſull of Rome, which was the father of the countrey, and as a king of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:9175:42"/>
the Romans, thought no leſſe in his heart, then <hi>Caligu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> did, that wiſhed Rome to haue but one neck, becauſe he might cut it off with one ſtroke: but that ſtroke fell vpon <hi>Caligulas</hi> necke: ſo ſuch cruell Tygers are often <note place="margin">Curt. lib. 7</note> made foode to feede fowles. Nothing is ſo ſtrong (ſaith <hi>Curtius)</hi> but ſometime the weakeſt may ouerthrowe it. We ſee the long &amp; great trees, that long were in grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in one howre to be cut downe.</p>
               <p>All Countreyes ought to bee purged and purifyed of theſe factious and ſeditious men, not as <hi>Naaman</hi> the Syrian was purifyed by waſhing in I ordan: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as <hi>Ezechias</hi> purifyed the Temple of Ieruſalem, but by a Militaty purification, and to ſacrifice ſuch fellowes by decimation, as <hi>Tamberlaine</hi> and <hi>Xerxes</hi> did.</p>
               <p>It is in <hi>Homer</hi> written of three kindes of purification: the one by fire, the other by water, the third by ayre: where mention is made of <hi>Vliſses,</hi> how hee commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <note place="margin">Odeſſ. 21.</note> that offences and great faultes ſhould bee purified with Brimſtone and fire, and with the ſlaughter of hogges, for a ſacrifice to the Gods.</p>
               <p>The like is of <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> who, after hee ſlew his mother <hi>Clitemneſtra,</hi> was ſo vexed with furies, that hee wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred like a madde man, vntill he was purified with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſent for from the Tracenians, and had from ſeuen ſeuerall riuers, and being put all together into a veſſell and waſhed ouer his body with that water, to purifie &amp; clenſe him, <hi>ex materna caede,</hi> of his mothers murthering. It ſhould ſeeme that <hi>Homer</hi> was acquainted with the cleanſing of <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> in the floud Iordan, of his leproſie; for they liued almoſt in one age.</p>
               <p>In purification and purging of falſe, deceitfull, and ſeditious Souldiers, the Generall, the Coronelles, the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:9175:42"/>
Captaines, and all the ſouldiers, all crowned with Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, <note place="margin">The pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of Campes.</note> ſhould in <hi>Martius</hi> field make ſuch ſupplications &amp; ſacrifices, as <hi>Ser. Tullius</hi> the third King of Rome had then conſtituted, which was a ſheepe, a Goate, a Sowe, and a Bull, at which time the Army ſhould haue a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine portion of corne, <hi>pro cuiuſque contubernio,</hi> for euery tenne Souldiers being of one company, and euery one ſhould haue a peece of money, called Drachma, with other ſuch military rewards, as were fit for euery com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to offer ioyntly their oblation &amp; ſacrifice for the purifying of their Army.</p>
               <p>In like ſort, if any great earthquake, lightning or thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring were, for the purifying &amp; purging of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries from ſeditious and mutinous people, either in the field amongſt Soldiers, or in their Cities amongſt Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, or in their Nauies vpon the Sea, they vſed many ceremonies.</p>
               <p>The baniſhing and purging of ſuch trecherous and ſeditious people, in Nauies on Seas, differed nothing, <note place="margin">The puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of Sea-Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</note> but in ſome ceremonies, which was, that many altars ſhould be made vpon the ſhore, and that altar which the water of the Sea had ſprinkled, the Prieſtes vpon that altar ſhould ſacrifice the offenders: then part of the ſacrifice ſhould be throwne into the Sea, the other bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpon the ſhore: this was the olde maner of the Romans in purifying and purging of wicked falſe men, from good men.</p>
               <p>They were ſo carefull, or rather ſuperſtitious, that if either an Owle, or a Wolfe had bin within the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of <hi>Iupiter</hi> in the Capitoll, <hi>ſacrificium peculare</hi> ſhould bee vſed. Many ſuch night-Owles, and many day-walking Wolues, come not onely into our Temples, but into our houſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:9175:43"/>
                  <hi>Scipio Emilianus,</hi> at what time hee was Cenſor, made <note place="margin">Scipio E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milianus.</note> no other ſupplication to the gods, but only for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of the city of Rome, and for purging of ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men out of the city of Rome.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Nero</hi> in his ſactifice &amp; ſupplication to the gods, made only mention of himſelfe and of the people, but not of the Senators and Magiſtrates. Too many are <note place="margin">Nero.</note> of <hi>Neroes</hi> nature, which would faine feed the peoples humours, to moue ſedition and mutinies, but generally they haue the like end as <hi>Nero</hi> had.</p>
               <p>Supplications and prayers were made amongſt the Pagans, for any victories or good ſucceſſe to any king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <note place="margin">Alex. lib. 5. cap. 27</note> or countrey. A decree was made in Rome, that the Citizens for fifteene dayes ſhould offer ſacrifice and ſupplications to the gods for the good ſucceſſe, that <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> had in his warres againſt the Gaules.</p>
               <p>So did <hi>Cicero</hi> being then Conſull, cauſe all the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators, Patricians, Tribes, with all the Citizens of Rome, Matrons, wiues, young and old, by themſelues crowned, to offer ſupplications and ſactifices in their <note place="margin">The purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe and victories.</note> Temples, celebrating ſolemne feaſtes, in token of great ioy and triumph, that the conſpiracy of <hi>Cateline</hi> was found out by <hi>Cicero,</hi> and his confederats vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by <hi>Luc. Antonius,</hi> then Conſull with <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like did <hi>Cicero</hi> for the victories and happy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of <hi>Oct. Caeſar.</hi> So did <hi>Dec. Brutus</hi> for the ioy and gladnes of the ouerthrow of <hi>Marc. Antonius</hi> at the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell at Mutina.</p>
               <p>The Grecians commonly neuer vſed ſupplication for any happines or fortunate ſucceſse, but playes and feaſts, but if it were ſome great victory ouer the enemy, or ſauing of their city from the enemy, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they would
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:9175:43"/>
with great pompe &amp; ſolemnity in their Temples offer ſacrifice and oblations, ſing Hymnes and Meeters, in yeelding thankes to their gods.</p>
               <p>The Athenians had alſo, ſaith <hi>Theopompus,</hi> euery fifth yere, as the Romans had their <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> ſo had they their <note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>i <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in Athens.</note> 
                  <hi>Panegyrys,</hi> their meeting in a Seſſion to giue thankes to their gods, with one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent, for the defending of Athe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s againſt the enemy: at which time, they made ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the people of <hi>Platea,</hi> their next neighbors, and of <hi>Chios,</hi> to the gods, to maintain the proſperous eſtate of their countrey, with banning and curſing of <hi>Philip</hi> and all his countrey Macedonia, with ſupplications to deſtroy his Nauies on the ſea, his Army vpon the land, <note place="margin">Alex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 5. cap. 77</note> his children and his family, as moſt deteſtable enemies vnto Greece: See the cate and loue the Heathens had of their countrey.</p>
               <p>The Greekes had alſo inſtructions of <hi>Epimenides,</hi> to purify their Cities in this ſort; to let two ſheepe, the one blacke, the other white, out of the townes end, and ſome man appointed to follow them, and where they would ſtay or lye, there would the Greekes offer obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſacrifice to their gods: this was their care for their countrey, and ſuch ſhould be the care of all good men towards their Countrey, to purge, to purify, and to weed all trecherous and ſeditious men as are neuer well, but either inuenting or doing ſome euill to their Country; not much vnlike to the purification of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> which you ſhall read hereafter.</p>
               <p>When the old Gaules purified or cleanſed their Cyties or Townes, their cuſtome was to feed one man <note place="margin">Of purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gaules.</note> moſt daintily for one whole yeere, and being full ſed
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:9175:44"/>
and fat, they led him round about the Citie or Towne vpon a ſolemne feaſt day, and after brought him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the City, and ſtoned him with ſtones to death, as a ſacrifice to purify their people.</p>
               <p>Such a cuſtome, as it ſeemeth, had the Iewes, when <hi>Pilate</hi> would haue had Chriſt deliuered, and let <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabas</hi> the murtherer dye according to their Lawes, the Iewes cried, Crucify Chriſt: they had rather haue <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabas</hi> a murtherer, then Chriſt a Sauiour.</p>
               <p>It ſeemed by <hi>Xerxes,</hi> which by lot of Decimation ſlue that Souldier, and deuided his bodie vnto two parts, to purify the army, that the Perſians vſed that kind of purging and cleanſing of their people which the Gaules did, and the Macedonians. The like law obſerued the Iewes, that one yeerely ſhould dye, to purify the people, as it ſeemed by <hi>Pilates</hi> ſpeach, when <hi>Barrabas</hi> was ſet free, and Chriſt died.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Elizeus</hi> the Prophet willed <hi>Naaman</hi> the Aſſyrian to goe and waſh himſelfe ſeuen times in the riuer Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan, <note place="margin">Elizeus.</note> and ſo he ſhould be clenſed of his Leproſy: but ſome practiſe with <hi>Gehezi,</hi> to deceyue their maſters. What ſhalbe their reward? The reward of <hi>Gehezi,</hi> the leproſy of <hi>Naaman</hi> for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moyſes</hi> was commanded from God, to put his owne ſiſter <hi>Miriam</hi> out of the hoſt for ſeuen dayes, vnul ſhe <note place="margin">Moyſes.</note> was purifyed by the Lawe, before ſhe ſhould be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued againe into the army.</p>
               <p>In another place <hi>Moyſes</hi> was commaunded, that the Iſraelites ſhould abſtayne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their wines, their clothes waſhed, before they ſhould approach neere the hill. So Chriſt in the new Teſtament willed the ten Lepers
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:9175:44"/>
to goe and ſhew themſelues vnto the Prieſt, according to the law of <hi>Moſes:</hi> but as they went, they were healed, and one came only to giue thanks vnto Chriſt.</p>
               <p>I doubt much, that neither <hi>Elizeus, Moyſes,</hi> nor Chriſt himſelfe can heale a nomber of their leproſy, where men are ſo falſe, that they can neither be true to their Prince, nor to their Country. Where ſhall men finde faith? What fire, what water can do good, when the fyre of heauen can not purify, and the water of life can not waſh them?</p>
               <p>The maner of purification by <hi>Moſes,</hi> was to kill a liue <note place="margin">Moſes pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification.</note> Sparrow ouer a fountaine of water, &amp; the Prieſt ſhould take Caedar wood, a Scarlet lace and Hyſſop, &amp; ſhould dip them with the liuing Sparrow in the bloud of the ſlaine Sparrow, and ſprinkle vpon him that was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, and ſo to bee purified. He that was cleanſed and purified by <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, ſhould waſh his clothes, and ſhaue off al his haire of his head, of his beard, and of his browes, and waſh himſelfe in water, and waſh his clothes, and be kept ſeuen dayes from the Camp. But concerning purification by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> of blacke ſpottes, ſcabbes, and vncleane iſſues, you may read the Leuiticall Lawes, how God would haue his people cleane, pure and ſound, both outward and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. <note place="margin">Leuit. 14.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Heathen were ſo ſuperſtitious in their ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of purifycation &amp; purging, that if any great earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, thunder, lightnings, or any monſtrous kind of births of men or of beaſts were in Rome, they ſhould be throwne into Tyber, or ſhould be ſlaine to be ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed, to appeaſe their countrey gods.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:9175:45"/>
There are many monſtrous births in diuers places and countries, that might be as well throwne into their owne country Riuers, as the Romanes did into Tiber, and ought farre better to bee drowned in their owne countryes, then the children of the Hebrues out of their countrie, by the Egyptians in Nylus.</p>
               <closer>Where I leaue, vntill I haue further time to write.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9175:45"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
